<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Adam in his innocencie. By William Bloys, esquire</title>
            <author>Bloys, William, 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1638</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 225 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 148 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B11637</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3139</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116391</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851608</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851608</idno>
            <idno type="VID">176251</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B11637)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 176251)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1299:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Adam in his innocencie. By William Bloys, esquire</title>
                  <author>Bloys, William, 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 279, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert Young, for George Lathum, at the signe of the Bishops head in Pauls Church yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1638.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Identified as STC 3139a on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Adam --  (Biblical figure) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:176251:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176251:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ADAM IN HIS INNOCENCIE.</p>
            <p>BY WILLIAM BLOYS, Eſquire.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Robert Young,</hi> for <hi>George Lathum,</hi> at the ſigne of the Biſhops head in Pauls Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard. 1638.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:176251:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:176251:2"/>
            <head>ADAM IN HIS INNOCENCIE</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore engaged my ſelfe to ſhew, how,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Medit on</hi> 42. <hi>Pſal. Ver.</hi> 6.</note> thoſe places that in themſelves are moſt delightfull, may by our good improvement be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come moſt profitable; Which I intended of the pleaſures of a Garden: the beſt fruit whereof will be, to carry up our thoughts into heaven. And this being the time wherein I ſee every thing put forth, I am admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:176251:3"/>to doe likewiſe, and thereby to diſcharge my promiſe.</p>
            <p>It may be thought a ſtrange enterpriſe and unad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed choice, to undertake this new diſcovery; and to attempt a reformation in that,
<note place="margin">Inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum duorum vitiotum, va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatis &amp; torporis, deſidioe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchrum. <hi>Lipſ.</hi>
               </note> which hath been the inſtrument of two vices, vaine Oſtentation, and dull Stupidity: wherein many doe offend, as by intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate eating of the fruit, to the prejudice of the health of their body; ſo likewiſe by exceſſive delight in affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted rarities, and fond cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſities, to the depravation of their mind: whereas if they were endued with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine wiſedome, and could reſtraine their extravagant deſires within the proper li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:176251:3"/>of reaſon and modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they might gather ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular contentment in the uſe thereof. It was the employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Adam</hi> in the eſtate of innocency, to dreſſe and keep the garden of Eden; which (in reſpect of the fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tility of the place) needed no husbandry; but that he might be a law to his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity. The knowledge of trees and herbes did well beſeem <hi>Solomon</hi> himſelfe, who was the wiſeſt of men. Having named him,
<note place="margin">Cyrus, Atta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus, Maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſſa, Cato, &amp;c.</note> it will be ſuperfluous to rehearſe other Kings &amp; Potentates, who have ſeriouſly addicted themſelves to this worke. <hi>Abraham</hi> would not plant a grove,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 21.33.</note> but hee would call upon the Name of the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting God; then much
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:176251:4"/>more ought we in planting an orchard (the apple tree ſo farre excelling the trees of the wood) to worſhip the Lord.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.3.</note> It pleaſed the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty to forbid his people to eate of the trees that they ſhould plant in the firſt three yeeres;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 20.20.</note> in which time the fruit was to be counted as uncircumciſed:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Levit.</hi> 19.23.</note> but in the fourth yeere all the fruit ſhould be holy to praiſe the Lord withall. During the time of their abſtinence they might conſider, that by reaſon of the ſin of man, who had corrupted his way, and filled the earth with violence and contagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, this good creature of God was not ſo pure unto them, but that it had need to be ſanctified by the word
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:176251:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>of God and by praier: and ever after, the firſt of the ripe fruits were to be offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red unto the Lord without delay. Yea,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.29.</note>
               <note place="margin">Nec ante guſtare quam diis conſecraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neb.</hi>
               </note> the very Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, when their fruit came to maturity, dared not ſo much as taſte of it, untill they had conſecrated ſome part thereof unto their gods. Should wee accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh this worke of plantati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on without ſeeking for a bleſſing, it were juſt with God to blaſt our endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours with barrenneſſe, that the trees of the Land ſhould not yeeld their fruits; or though they doe, that wee ſhould not gather them; or though we doe, that we ſhould not eate of them. The ſtory is not unknowne of him,
<note place="margin">Ancaeus in Na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Com. Mythol.</note> who gave occaſion
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:176251:5"/>to that Proverbe,
<note place="margin">Senex in Perotto.</note> Many things fall between the cup and the lip: Or laſtly, though we did brutiſhly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voure them, without look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up to the giver, God may puniſh our uſurpation, as hee did the exceſſe of <hi>Noah:</hi> they may be in the mouth as honey for ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but bitterneſſe in the end. To avoid theſe puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and to obtaine Gods bleſſing upon us in all that we ſet our hands unto, let us labour to make an holy uſe of the creatures, and to be heavenly minded in all our actions.</p>
            <p>It was anciently thought,
<note place="margin">Hortoſque contra invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentium ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſcinatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes dicari videmus. <hi>Plin. Sec.</hi>
               </note> that gardens had a ſpeciall immunity againſt the charmes and machinations of the malignant: If wee
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:176251:5"/>could exalt our ſelves in theſe high contemplations, that infernall Serpent ſhould never fold himſelfe about us. It is reported of <hi>Caeſar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ut aſſectato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem à ſe ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legaret. <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neb.</hi>
               </note> that he ſelected a garden re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote from the city, being on the other ſide of the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, that he might free him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe from petitioners and attendants: It will be our greateſt wiſedome in theſe places to retire into our ſelves, laying aſide thoſe waighty cares and troubles, whereby we are preſſed downe, lifting up our hearts unto the Lord; looking un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt, and he alſo will looke upon us in mercy, and behold us under the tree, as he did <hi>Nathaniel.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 1.48.</note> And as <hi>Amos,</hi> being a gatherer of Sycomore fruit, was taken
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:176251:6"/>to be made a Prophet of the Lord, unto whom he revealed his ſecret; ſo we ſhall come to be more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly inſtructed in the good pleaſure of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The inviſible things of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.20.</note> 
               <hi>that is, his eternall power and Godhead, are ſeen by the creation of the world, being conſidered in his workes.</hi> Mans ſpeciall voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was the ſtudy of the creatures, wherein hee might diſcerne the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the Creatour. There is plentifull variety of good meditations obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to every beleever, and able to ſatisfie the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding with endleſſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment. The great vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume of nature, the book of the creatures is laid open
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:176251:6"/>before us; and in every leafe, and page, and line of it, God hath imprinted ſuch evident characters of his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine properties, ſuch-lively repreſentations of his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that we may runne and reade his excellency there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145.10.</note> 
               <hi>All thy workes ſhall praiſe thee, O Lord, and thy Saints ſhall bleſſe thee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they ſhall ſpeake of the glory of thy Kingdome, and talke of thy power.</hi> Thus every good Chriſtian, being a tree of righteouſneſſe of the Lords planting, is full of ſap, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleniſhed with the influence of that gracious Spirit, and filled with prudence, duely to ponder the infinite maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie and incomprehenſible greatneſſe of God, by thoſe viſible expreſſions, which
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:176251:7"/>are continually preſented unto him: The ungodly are not ſo, but, as if they had eaten of the fruit of the Lote-tree (which made them that eate of it to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get their native country) they remember not whoſe off-ſpring they are,
<note place="margin">Dulcedine Loti lique<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat &amp; patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am. <hi>Alciat.</hi>
               </note> they be unmindfull of the celeſtiall Jeruſalem, which is the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of us all: and doe as much neglect to ſeek that heavenly Canaan, as <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> did to returne to Haran from whence he came. Theſe may fitly be compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red unto that bird,
<note place="margin">Humi ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quo caſu de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſi, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>podes nullo negotio ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piuntur. <hi>Scal. in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt.</hi>
               </note> which if by any caſualty it happened to be upon the ground, it was readily taken, as not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to raiſe it ſelfe: In like manner they are readily overwhelmed by the ſnare
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:176251:7"/>of the fowler, while they ſubject themſelves to the love of the world, and the things of the world.
<note place="margin">Velut ſi prolapſus cecidiſſet, terran oſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo contigit. <hi>Liv. Ant. Muret. Var. Lect.</hi>
               </note> And as <hi>Brutus,</hi> by direction of the Oracle, did caſt himſelf downe, and kiſſe the earth, that he might come to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verne; ſo they regard not before whom they doe fall downe and worſhip, that wealth and power may be given unto them. It is rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of a covetous wretch, that he moſt corruptly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted that place in the Pſalme, where it is ſaid, <hi>The earth hath hee given to the children of men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 115.16.</note> as a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible allegation for his gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy purſuit after worldly commodities; whereas if we did rightly weigh it, we might be excited to bleſſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:176251:8"/>the Lord for his bounty, in filling the earth with his goodneſſe, and giving it to the ſonnes of men, who are educated at Gods foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoole (as <hi>Paul</hi> at the feet of <hi>Gamaliel</hi>) where we have many good things,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 22.3.</note> many vertuous inſtructions com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted unto us, which we by the help of the holy Ghoſt ought to keep for our future comfort. And now ſpeaking of the earth, I am come to the foundation upon which I muſt erect my future diſcourſe; deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to have the ſoile well prepared, that ſo there may ariſe the more fruit and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit by this enſuing Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt then (that I may proceed the more metho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dically,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:176251:8"/>being to extract mine obſervations out of a place of order, and not out of an intricate wilderneſſe of confuſed wandring,) in the beginning of our egreſſe and ſtepping forth, that there may be an enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the mind as well as of the body, even in that motion and exerciſe of the body manifold good thoughts may accompany us: and as we walke out for our refreſhing, ſo our heart,
<note place="margin">Palpitat, &amp; quaſi alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum movetur animal. <hi>Plin. Sec.</hi>
               </note> which is as another crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ever ſtirring within us, may be directed unto the Lord, and may draw nigh unto him, through faith in Chriſt, who is the only way that leads unto the Father; We have great cauſe to praiſe the Lord, who hath
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:176251:9"/>given us ſtrength and liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie thus to walke: He did, as hee ſpeaketh of <hi>Ephraim,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 11.3.</note> teach us to goe, taking us by the armes, and guiding us in our unſtable yeeres, preſerving us from the fall and lameneſſe of <hi>Mephibo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam</hi> 4.4.</note> He hath kept us ever ſince from any exceeding great diſeaſe in our feet,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16.12.</note> as <hi>Aſa</hi> had: we doe not right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſider Gods love here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. If we had been ſmitten, and after received ſtrength, wee would enter into the Temple, leaping and prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing God,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 3.8.</note> as the man did, who was lame from the wombe, and raiſed by <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> Hee hath delivered us from the reſtraint which <hi>Joſeph</hi> endured,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105.18.</note> whoſe feet were hurt with fetters: yea,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:176251:9"/>he hath given us a pleaſant path to walke in, having be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed many bleſſings and comforts upon us: whereas others, as well deſerving, have their waies beſet with briers, doe meet with many croſſes and encumbrances. He hath ſent us the light to walke in, that we may di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcerne whither we goe; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving rightly informed our judgements, that we might eſchew errours, and walke before him in truth with all our heart: whereas others are in darkneſſe, and have many ſtumbling-blockes in their way; their evill trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled conſcience being poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt with many impertinent ſcruples, inſomuch that they walke like them that were to be tried by Fire-ordeal,
<note place="margin">Verſtegan.</note>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:176251:10"/>who being blind-folded, did paſſe over many glow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hot irons; they feare e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſtep they ſet to fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſome inevitable danger. Now in our going out, and returning back, there ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to be ſome reſemblance with the life of man,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal</hi> 104.23.</note> who <hi>goeth forth unto his worke, and to his labour untill the evening.</hi> He entreth into the world in his child-hood, where he meets with much commotion and agitation: After which he beginneth to ebbe, and retire in his old age: Having aſcended the hill of his full ſtrength, he then deſcends and walkes through the valley of the ſhadow of death,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 23.4.</note>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 2.2.</note> which is the way of all the earth, as <hi>Joſhuah</hi> call'd it,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joſh.</hi> 23.14.</note> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:176251:10"/>conducted the people into the Land of the living, who then ſhewed them the way to their reſt, where they ſhould ſleep in the duſt. Man is alwaies going to his long home; as well in the ſweet walkes of recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as in the tedious jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of important neceſſity; as well in the ſmooth allies of joyfull contentment, as in the deep and difficult road of vexation and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row. In our walkes our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are not alwaies towards the riſing, but ſometimes we looke towards the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining Sunne; and thereby we may be put in mind to ſet our faces, as though we would goe to Jeruſalem,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 9.53.</note> &amp; to prepare for that time, when we ſhall lye downe in
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:176251:11"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:176251:11"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:176251:12"/>darkneſſe; which that we may doe, we ought ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to conſider, whether it be a good and a ſtraight way that we walke in, or not. No man will take ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny turns in an uncouth path that is inconvenient for his paſſage, being overgrowne with weeds and buſhes, or offenſive to his ſenſes, by reaſon of evill ſavours, and hatefull objects: And yet how many be there that go on, yea that run head-long in the dangerous waies bringing them to deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? The drunkard ſtaggers in the broad way that he makes to be defiled: The adulterer goeth an obſcure ſhady way in the evening,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 7.9.</note> in the twilight, that he may not be diſcovered: The ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortioner
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:176251:12"/>walketh in crook<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed waies: The ambitious climbeth up the rocky way, whoſe feet ſtand in ſlippery places: The covetous man goeth in a by-way, on the other ſide with the Levite,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 10.32.</note> that he might avoid occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to exerciſe charity. All theſe are impure and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane waies, and they that walke in them may rightly be ſaid to goe in the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorous way, tending to ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and confuſion, while they violently preſſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in wickedneſſe.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 13.24</note> There was a Lion in the Prophets way, that ſlew him for his diſobedience: there is roar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Lion, watching to kill and devoure all thoſe, which runne aſtray in theſe diſconſolate waies going
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:176251:13"/>downe to the chambers of death. As the people ſtood ſtill in the way when they came to the place where <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſa</hi> was ſlaine;
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20.12</note> ſo it will behoove us, when we ſee how many have miſcarried, and periſhed by wandring in theſe waies of miſery, not to proceed any further therein, but to ſtep into that good and upright way, whereby we may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted into eternall life. It is a dreadfull ſigne of Gods diſpleaſure, when he ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth any man to walke on proſperouſly in his ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne way and ungodly councell, as in an even alley, without any obſtacles or impediments, not ſending his meſſenger to ſtop him in his ſinfull courſe. It were
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:176251:13"/>much better that the Lord ſhould hedge up our way with thornes, and make a wall that we ſhould not find our pathes,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.6.</note> than to permit us to runne greedily after licentious errours:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 23.3.</note> 
               <hi>Bleſſed is the man whom God leadeth in the pathes of righteouſneſſe for his names ſake:</hi> He doth alwaies <hi>heare a voice behind him, ſaying: This is the way,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.21.</note> 
               <hi>walke in it.</hi> Having once en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the way of truth, we muſt perſevere in it, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies going on cheerfully, without fainting or weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; like the Cherubims in <hi>Ezechiel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezech.</hi> 1.9.</note> which went ſtraight forward, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned not againe: Although in our walkes we goe firſt forward, and then turne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine; yet in this paſſage we
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:176251:14"/>muſt proceed conſtantly, without turning backe;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 9.62.</note> for then we are not fit for the Kingdome of God. Having begun well, who ſhould hinder us from perſiſting in our obedience? It had been better not to have knowne this way, than having knowne it,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.21.</note> to turne from the commandement delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red unto us.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 5.22.</note> Did <hi>Enoch</hi> walke with God three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred ſixty and five yeeres? and ſhall not we walke in his ordinances the ſhort terme of our life, which is but a ſpan long? He had a ſpacious ground to walke in, of a vaſt extent like Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe it ſelfe; whereas we are concluded within nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row bounds, and can never goe farre, but that we are
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:176251:14"/>called backe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90.3.</note> 
               <hi>Returne yee children of men.</hi> Although we cannot keep pace with him, and <hi>Abraham,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 24.40. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.9.</note> and <hi>David,</hi> yet if we walke in the ſteps of their faith and obedience, we ſhall in the end finiſh our courſe with joy: In the meane time,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.12.</note> as we are preſerved from diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement; ſo we muſt be awakened from ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: there ought to be a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall preſſing forward in the good way; By uſing our legges in walking, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the more fit and able to performe that exerciſe: So we, ſetting our ſelves in the right way, it pleaſeth the Lord to eſtabliſh our go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and to ſtrengthen us for the better diſcharge of all holy duties. We walke
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:176251:15"/>with ſpeed and agility, when we deſire to obtaine heate thereby; ſo there muſt be a cheerfull forwardneſſe in Gods ſervice, and a fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent zeale after his glory, that our hearts may be warmed by his grace, &amp; our ſoules refreſhed by his love.</p>
            <p>Thus by revolving ſuch pious thoughts in our minds, we may be preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from evill; as the ſea by its fluctuation is kept from putrefaction:
<note place="margin">Hic motus aquas maris à putrefacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one tuetur. <hi>Magir.</hi>
               </note> but how few be there who retire in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their owne hearts, when they goe forth into their walkes? and doe more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the influence of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to come upon them,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.16.</note> as the North wind (purging them from the infectious ſettlings of corruption) and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:176251:15"/>to blow upon them as the South wind (watering their roots by ſweet ſhowers) that their graces as ſpices may flow out, than they do the gentle breath of coole aire for the refreſhing of their bodies?</p>
            <p>It is the common practice of moſt men in the very beginning of their daies, to enter into an intricate Maze of endleſſe wandring, walking on every ſide,
<note place="margin">Impii am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulant in circuitu. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 12.8.</note> as the Pſalmiſt ſpeakes, Run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning round in a circulation untill they waxe giddy, and fall into extreme perill: or elſe be as farre in the end from any true reſt and ſolid comfort, as they were in the beginning.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi> 1.7.</note> It was the Divels vagrant courſe to go to and fro in the earth, and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:176251:16"/>to walke up and downe in it: Whom doe theſe men chuſe for their leader, while they ſubject them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to theſe ſerpentine windings; being involved and invironed with the tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulent affaires of this life, out of which they know not how to extricate and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold themſelves? and yet they thinke their way to be ſafe, while they ſeeke to compaſſe their deſignes in this turning Labyrinth, when as they have never ſet foot into the path of life, but are as farre from arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving at the port of bliſſe, as they be from good ſucceſs, who would preſſe thorow the North-weſt paſſage; and at laſt (if ever) returne backe with nought but
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:176251:16"/>emptineſſe and deſolation. Theſe men ſeem to be dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven with the unſettled er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of <hi>Copernicus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Quod terra moveatur, &amp; ſol ſit omnis motus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers. <hi>Clavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us.</hi>
               </note> who thought that the earth did move, and the ſunne ſtood ſtill; ſo they are whirled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with the world, and doe compaſſe ſea and land for gaine, or to accompliſh their deſignes; but they ſtirre not in purſuit of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly bleſſings,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4.</note> their minds being blinded by the god of this world, leſt the light of the glorious Goſpel of Chriſt, who is the Image of God, ſhould ſhine unto them; like the Egyptians,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 10.23.</note> which roſe not from their place in the three daies of thicke darkneſſe; ſo they, during the three daies of their youth, middle age,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:176251:17"/>and old age, never rouze up themſelves to ſeeke for the treaſure in heaven, or to diſcover the ſweet light of Gods Word; whereas they make haſte to obtaine the fading benefits of this tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitory life with ſuch violent forwardneſſe, that the ſwift pace of <hi>Aſahel</hi> or <hi>Jehu</hi> doth not exceed their furious ſpeed: Having ſpent their breath, and tired themſelves in following this ſhadow that flyes away from them, it were their onely happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to conſider their er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous waies: And as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi> did cut that knot he was not able to untie; ſo if they can find no place where they may goe forth, then to breake the circle, and free themſelves from
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:176251:17"/>that reſtleſſe ſucceſſion of worldly cares, in which they were before entan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled;
<note place="margin">Homines ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi moleſti? Hic apud te eris; Occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patio ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſit? hic replevere. <hi>Lipſ.</hi>
               </note> and having eſcaped thoſe tumults and vexati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, whereby they former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly waſted their vigour, and conſumed their beſt ſtrength, now to repoſe themſelves under the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of the Almighty,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91.1.</note> as in an arbour of reſt and refre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing, where they may caſt off thoſe tedious moleſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which formerly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed them: and being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted from the throng of the multitude,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal</hi> 4.4.</note> may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune with their own heart, and ſo come to diſcern that ſore travell, wherewith all they are exerciſed under the Sunne, who ſpend their vain life as a ſhadow, and their
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:176251:18"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:176251:18"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:176251:19"/>daies in ſorrow and griefe, while they ſeeke after lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Judg.</hi> 9.15.</note> and truſt unto the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of <hi>Jothams</hi> bramble, that will rend and teare them; or of <hi>Manaſſes</hi> thornes,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 33.11. <hi>Jonah</hi> 4.7.</note> that will deceive them; or of <hi>Jonas</hi> gourd, that will ſoon forſake them, placing their confidence in the inſtable benefits of this life, which before the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning may be dried up from the roots, like the barren figge-tree:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mar.</hi> 11.20. <hi>Luke</hi> 12.20.</note> 
               <hi>Thou foole, this night thy ſoule ſhall be requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of thee; then whoſe ſhall thoſe things be that thou haſt provided?</hi> Such as relye up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe outward helpes, for the fruition of good, and protection from evill, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare plainly from what ſtocke they are come, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:176251:19"/>that they be the off-ſpring of <hi>Adam,</hi> the common root of mankind, who, after his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion againſt Gods word, did thinke to hide himſelfe from the preſence of the Lord among the trees of the garden; whoſe example might occaſion the Jewes to report, that <hi>Cain</hi> his ſonne, after he had ſinned, and had drunke the dregges of the cup of trembling, did lurke in ſecret places among the trees and buſhes, and ſo was killed like a beaſt by the hand of <hi>Lamech.</hi> But could <hi>Adam</hi> thinke by the great knowledge hee had lately acquired, to hide himſelfe in that thicke covert from Gods all-ſeeing eye? Or how dare he approach ſo nigh unto the trees, when
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:176251:20"/>the ſound of a ſhaken leafe might chaſe him,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Levit.</hi> 26.36.</note> and make him flee, as fleeing from a ſword, even from that fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming ſword, which after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward was placed to keep him out of Paradiſe? Did he reſolve with <hi>Jacob</hi> to go downe into his grave? and having deſerved that the terrible ſentence of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould be ſpeedily executed upon him, hee would in that obſcure ſhade compoſe himſelfe for his death and buriall? but hee might not be freed ſo ſoon from his horrour; death then fled from him, as hee from God, though at laſt it turn'd againe like <hi>Abner,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.23.</note> and ſmote him to the ground. Could he imagine in that ſecret place to be co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:176251:20"/>from the Divine ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance? as if God that planted the garden ſhould not know the moſt private and utmoſt parts thereof: Surely,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.15.</note> hee made lyes his refuge, and under falſhood hee hid himſelfe.
<note place="margin">Stat pervia nullis ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus. <hi>Statius.</hi> Nulli pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trabilis aſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o Lucus erat. <hi>Ovid.</hi>
               </note> Though ſome trees may defend from the ſcorching heate of the Sunne, Gods eyes are brighter than the Sunne, and darkneſſe hideth not from him, but the night ſhineth as the day; the darkneſſe and the light are both alike to him. The Lord, who plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the eare and formed the eye, heard that ſweet coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell which he and <hi>Eve</hi> did take in this their deſolate miſery, and ſaw their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, whereof they themſelves were ſenſible:
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:176251:21"/>and yet ſuch was their bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh ſtupidity (when they loſt their underſtanding, and became as the beaſt that pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſheth) that they thought to cover that from God, which was ſo openly diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered unto themſelves. They ſaw the tree was to be deſired to make one wiſe; but they found not ſuch operation therin: O ye fools, when wil ye be wiſe? The wiſdome they gained therby deſcended not from above, but was earthy, ſenſuall, divelliſh: They ſaw it was pleaſant to the eye; but why would they looke upon that, which was not lawfull for them to eate? and what fruit had they in that, whereof they are now aſhamed? They ſaw it was
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:176251:21"/>good for food, when as the deadlieſt poyſon in the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent had not been ſo hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. There is mention of one <hi>Gruvelius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Obiit im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proviſo lap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu ex arbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, cum filio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis pyrum vellet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerpere. <hi>Graſſerus in Poem.</hi>
               </note> who gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſome fruit for his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to eate, by a fall did kill himſelfe; but our pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents eating this fruit, by their fall did not only break and diſſolve themſelves, but did grind their poſterity to powder: for duſt we are,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.19.</note> and unto duſt we ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne. When they were in the midſt of the garden, as taking ſureſt poſſeſſion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing farre remote from the border and bounds, in grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ſecurity, not obſerving where their enemy might enter to deprive them of their happineſſe, then were they nigheſt unto ejection
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:176251:22"/>and exile, being ready to be caſt out of their native ſoile, into a curſed land made bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren for the wickedneſſe of them that were to dwell therein; where they did, &amp; we their children through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all generations ever ſhal continue ſtrangers and pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grims, having no abiding city. In the beginning God tooke the man, and put him into the garden of Eden, having made him in his owne image and likeneſſe, full of majeſty and beauty, not needing any garments, which though they had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded the royaltie of <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> yet might not be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with that illuſtrious ſplendour &amp; dignity which ſhined in <hi>Adam:</hi> But after he had deveſted himſelfe of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:176251:22"/>this excellency, and ſtript himſelfe naked and bare, like a dry tree, or a withered branch, when all things which were dainty and goodly were departed from him, then his glory was tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into corruption, and his comelieſt parts had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundant uncomelineſs. The branches of the trees were an excellent bower to ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him; and a few figge leaves, or the skins of beaſts were the beſt garments to clothe him. Thus this good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tree,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.11.</note> whoſe height rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched unto heaven (like that in the viſion) who would have been as God, knowing good and evill, was hewne downe, and muſt have been caſt into the fire to have burned evermore, like <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:176251:23"/>buſh, and never to have conſumed; but Chriſt our Redeemer, the root and off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring of <hi>David,</hi> did inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe between him and Gods anger:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 1.78.</note> The Branch from on high hath viſited us;
<note place="margin">Non ficut a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia ſunt ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mina, quae à terra germi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. <hi>Beza.</hi> Nazaret ab Hebraeorum voce, quam alii ſurcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum, alii flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretantur. <hi>Cauſabon.</hi>
               </note> This Nazarene was plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted here upon earth; Hee humbled himſelfe, and was found in the likeneſſe of man, being a Tree of life in raiſing the dead, continually yeelding fruit better than gold, yea than fine gold, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies doing good, and fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the hungry with good things: Whoſe leaves were for the healing of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; who did communicate his vertue to them that came under his ſhadow, ſeeking for help, curing the diſeaſes of the body, and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:176251:23"/>the infirmities of the ſoule: Yet this fruitfull bough (prefigured by <hi>Joſeph</hi>) was ſorely grieved,
<note place="margin">Sub hoe ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po depicta eſt nobis imago Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti. <hi>Calvin.</hi>
               </note> and ſhot at by the archers; hee was wounded and pierced in many parts and members of his body, and the bloud came forth at the breaches that they made in this Vine:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lam.</hi> 1.12. Vindemiavit me. <hi>The Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Wint. Paſsion Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
               </note> He was bereft of the dry leaves, of humane com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts; of the green leaves, his Diſciples which forſook him; and of the fruit of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine conſolation. The tree was hewne downe, the branches cut off, the leaves ſhaken off, and the fruit ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered: If this was done to the green tree, what ſhould have been done to the dry? If Chriſt our Surety were thus afflicted, we who were
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:176251:24"/>the objects of hatred, and ſubjects of wrath, muſt have been pluckt up and deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for ever, without Gods mercy towards us herein: But there is hope of a tree, if it be cut downe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job.</hi> 14.7.</note> that it will ſprout againe, and that the tender branch thereof will not ceaſe; Chriſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcends from the lower parts of the earth: He doth ariſe in the garden, God not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering his Holy One to ſee corruption.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mar.</hi> 4.27.</note> As the ſeed caſt into the ground doth ſpring and grow up, the husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man knowes not how; ſo though it be beyond the hope, beſides the beliefe, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the apprehenſion of the Apoſtles, Chriſt being dead is againe quickened, and become a beautifull
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:176251:24"/>and glorious branch,
<note place="margin">Quam mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos aeſtu la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borantes, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morum opa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citas texit? <hi>Senec.</hi>
               </note> a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge from the ſtorme, a ſhadow from the heat, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecting us from his Fathers wrath, when by our provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations it begins to be kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled againſt us: From him we receive this bleſſed fruit, that in peace and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity we can ſit every man under his vine,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Micah</hi> 4.4.</note> and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his figge-tree,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zech.</hi> 3.10.</note> that in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundant plenty we can eate every one of his vine, and every one of his figge-tree; that in perfect charity we can call every man his neighbour under his vine,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 36.16.</note> and under his figge-tree: whoſe love doth not deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine in the outward bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits of this life; for then our ſhadow would be turned into darkneſſe: but he gives
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:176251:25"/>us the gracious promiſes of a better life, when the times of Refreſhing ſhall come from the preſence of the Lord,
<note place="margin">Tempora refrigerii. <hi>Acts</hi> 3.19.</note> that, the Sun ſhall not any more light on us, nor any heat: Theſe are the bleſſings we ſhould chiefly ſeek after, which will never leave us, nor forſake us; as for the delights and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of this life, they are like a fleeting ſhadow, of no continuance: If God blowes upon them, they doe wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and fade like a leafe. In the calme and bright dayes of Summer, wee receive ſome contentment by uſing our arbours; but when the ſtorme ariſeth, or the Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter approacheth, or the day groweth to an end, we then returne into our houſes. In
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:176251:25"/>the time of health and ſtrength, wee are ready to ſay, I ſhall never be moved, and doe place too much confidence in the profits and comforts of the world; but when God ſhall ſend ſome pining ſickneſſe, that ſhall ſhake us like a mighty tempeſt; when the winter of old age cauſeth our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to faile, and the yeeres are come in which we have no pleaſure; when the night doth overtake us, and we goe to the gates of the grave, even to the land of darkneſſe, and of the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of death; we ſhall then be removed like a ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards tent, our earthly houſe of this tabernacle ſhall be diſſolved, and we ſhall arrive at our long
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:176251:26"/>home (as <hi>Barzillai</hi> was bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in the grave of his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents) where we may ſay to corruption,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.37</note> 
               <hi>Thou art my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and to the worme, Thou art my mother, and my ſiſter.</hi> Oh that we were wiſe, that we underſtood this, that we would conſider our latter end; and not ſet our hearts upon theſe tranſitory trifles that deceive us when wee have greateſt need of them: Thinke upon the renowned Patriarkes and obedient Rechabites (bleſſed of the Lord) who dwelt in tents; it was but the plucking up of a pin, and they were gone.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 120. Indeſinenter vagare, &amp; errare co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor. <hi>Jun. Job</hi> 27.18.</note> Though thou liveſt in an houſe of Cedar, it is but as the tents of Kedar, or a booth that the keeper maketh, as <hi>Job</hi> ſpeakes, or a
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:176251:26"/>lodge in a garden, often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, or of ſhort conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance: God can ſweep a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way thy web with the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of deſtruction; or cut thee off, and make thee goe to the generation of thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, where thou ſhalt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſee light.</p>
            <p>We will not abide any longer in this our arbour, the uſe whereof doth ſo expire.</p>
            <p>Now, becauſe a planta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is vaine, unleſſe it be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vironed with a ſufficient de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence againſt the beaſt of the field that deſtroies the trees,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.15.</note> as the little foxes ſpoile the vines; and againſt the beaſt of Epheſus, bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh and unreaſonable men, who will not be content to eate their fill at their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:176251:27"/>(as God did permit in our neighbours vineyard) but will put into their veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.24.</note> robbing the owner of the fruit of his labour: we will therefore in the next place walke about our gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and goe round about it, marking well her walls, and conſidering the ſtrength of her incloſure, by meanes whereof it is preſerved from ruine and deſolation. In the Parables,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.33.</note> when God plants a vineyard, he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides for the ſafety thereof, either hedging it round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.2.</note> or making a wall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it; thereby declaring his providence and care in the preſervation of his Church and Choſen:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 27.3.</note> Leſt any hurt his vineyard, hee will keep it night and day:
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:176251:27"/>
               <hi>As the mountaines are round about Jeruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 125.2.</note> 
               <hi>ſo the Lord is round about his people, from henceforth even for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver:</hi> Thus hee made an hedge about <hi>Job,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi> 1.10.</note> and about his houſe, and about all that he had: thus he doth compaſſe us about with his loving kindneſſe, and keeps us from the adverſaries of ſoule and body. We have a vigilant enemy, ever ready to aſſault us: he walkes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, as <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeakes,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.8.</note> and would take any advantage to make a breach, and enter, as he did into <hi>Judas:</hi> And having once climbed up, and got poſſeſſion, like a thiefe he would ſteale, and kill, and deſtroy; robbing us of the fruit of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and depriving us of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:176251:28"/>all heavenly comforts, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king us to become a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, a waſte, and a curſe. Now it is by the favour and goodneſſe of God that we are protected,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.12.</note> as a garden incloſed, a ſpring ſhut up, a fountaine ſealed: The An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel of the Lord encampeth round about them that feare him, and delivereth them; wherefore let us feare to offend againſt the Lord: for in ſo doing we lay our ſelves open to the rage and cruelty of all our enemies. There are divers kinds of plants that will get rooting in the joynts of walls and buildings,
<note place="margin">Caprificus, ficus, hede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra, &amp; alia virgulta. <hi>Cauſabon.</hi>
               </note> and there increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, will breake them aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and overthrow them: Such are our ſinnes, if we ſuffer them to grow up, and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:176251:28"/>doe cheriſh them, they will batter downe the wall, and expoſe us to confuſion. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver remember that there is no ſtrength nor fortification that can ſecure us againſt the judgements of God, when wee tranſgreſſe his lawes: If hee gives power unto man to leap over a wall,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.29.</note> then he himſelfe is moſt able to ſurprize us whereſoever wee bee. Though our foundation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bideth ſure, the God of hoſts can muſter up his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, the locuſts,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 10.15.</note> the pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer-worme, the caterpiller,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amos</hi> 4.9.</note> the canker-worm, the froſt,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joel</hi> 1.4, 7.</note> blaſting, and the like, to eate the fruit of the trees, and conſume the increaſe of our labour. No mighty man can be delivered by much
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:176251:29"/>ſtrength: God can take him away as with a whirlewind both living and in his wrath. As we are to be ſenſible of Gods love towards our ſelves in particular; ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe we ought evermore to be thankfull for his won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull mercy and unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able goodneſſe towards this his Church, which he hath hitherto ſo graciouſly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved. There is a City that is deſcribed to be compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed about with fire,
<note place="margin">Silicum la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidicinae, unde cin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum igne Madritum. <hi>Mercator.</hi>
               </note> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the quarries of flint adjoyning thereunto: But I am ſure the Lord hath been unto us a wall of fire round about;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zech.</hi> 2.5.</note> and not of fire only, but as the waters were a wall unto the Iſraelites on the right hand,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.22.</note> and on the left; ſo he hath ſurrounded
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:176251:29"/>us with his favourable pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection on every ſide; whoſe providence and love to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us have been a ſurer defence than a wall of braſs could have been: When our cruell enemies beſet us round, and thought to have laid waſte defenced Cities into ruinous heapes; God knew their rage againſt us, and their tumult came up into his eares; he put a hook into the noſe of that great Leviathan, and a bridle into his lips, driving him whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he pleas'd, and turn'd him backe, though not by the ſame way by which he came: Since that, there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſe a generation, who were the Serpents in this our Paradiſe, full of all ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty and all miſchiefe; ſuch
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:176251:30"/>as attempted to beat through a ſtone wall, to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrow the foundation,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Winter in Biſhop</hi> Carl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance.</hi>
               </note> to ſtrike at the root (as one of them ſpake) to overturne and diſſipate the Royall ſtate, and chiefe ſupportati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Land: but God turned their councell into fooliſhneſſe; they who were folden together as thornes, and ſtrengthened them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in their wickedneſſe, are devoured as ſtubble ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dry: The Lord did pluck them out of their dwelling place, and root them out of the land of the living; Now praiſed be the Name of the Lord for theſe former deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verances, and bleſſed be the Lord for the benefits and comforts, which at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent wee doe enjoy, that
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:176251:30"/>peace and proſperity that are within the walls and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laces of this our Sion, and above all, that our Land doth flow with the ſincere milke of the Word, and we have the righteous judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, which are ſweeter than honey and the honey-combe; without which, though our Vines did bring forth cluſters, like them at Eſhcol,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Numb.</hi> 13.23</note> though we had abundance of all out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward helpes, yet we were moſt miſerable. In former times there have been ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold rebellions and inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections in the Land; when the trees would annoint a King over them; the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects would depoſe one, and exalt another: and though England were then a gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:176251:31"/>of deliciouſneſſe unto the Popes,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Innocent.</hi> 4. Hortus deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciarum, &amp; puteus inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſtus. <hi>Abbot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Hill.</hi>
               </note> as one of them boaſted, and a faire flower in their garland; yet in it ſelf it was a vally of ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, where thouſands did fall on the right hand, and ten thouſand on the left. And beſides them which were cut off in the civill wars; as in the deſtruction of the Moabites,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 3.19.</note> every faire and good tree was felled; ſo here ſome of the moſt fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and godly were hewen down as unprofitable trees, and caſt into the fire:
<note place="margin">Fruſtrà di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens folia decuti, ramu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſculos am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putari; Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicem hanc, &amp; Haereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum ſpem unicam ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cindendam. <hi>Biſhop God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>win.</hi>
               </note> Yea that cruell GARDINER, who then raged, could not be ſatisfied with ſhreading off ſo many branches, but he would have laid the axe to the root, and have taken away the life of <hi>Her,</hi> who
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:176251:31"/>was overſhadowed by the rich mercies of the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that ſhe might afterward excell all the Daughters in doing vertuouſly, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a refuge for them in diſtreſſe: Since the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of whoſe reigne, our Kingdome hath been as a watered garden,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.11.</note> and like a ſpring of waters: Our ſpeares have been turned into pruning-hookes,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mic.</hi> 4.3.</note> and here have been the happy Iſlands,
<note place="margin">Apud Grae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum Gram. reperi Inſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las Fortuna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas in Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunia eſſe, ubi frondent arbores, &amp;c. <hi>Muretus.</hi>
               </note> where all things have flouriſhed in excellent beauty and perfection. So long as we have the dew of Heaven, we may expect the fatneſſe of the earth; while we have the Sunne, we may hope for precious fruits to be brought forth thereby; while we have the Word
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:176251:32"/>of truth, we may hope for the bleſſings that do attend upon the ſame. But as there was a figge-tree,
<note place="margin">Quamdiu ea viveret, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertatem pop. Rom. incolumem manſuram. <hi>Feſtus &amp; Joſ. Scal.</hi>
               </note> which was ominous to the Romanes, if it withered; ſo there is a Vine, that the Lord brought out of Egypt, and hath planted it amongſt us, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing it to take deep root, and fill the Land: If this be laid waſte, we may juſtly feare the anger of the Lord; if wee (being freed from the darkneſſe of Popery) ſhall become unfruitfull, we may looke for judgement and fiery indignation. Where God beſtowes great coſt,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 20.</note> he requires fruit proportiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.</note> if we be planted as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a wall, where the heat of the Sunne is more ſtrong and united; if we
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:176251:32"/>have powerfull meanes to helpe us forward in produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing good fruit, and yet continue barren, then our ſinnes will ſoon be ripened thereby, like the basket of ſummer fruit which <hi>Amos</hi> ſaw;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amos</hi> 8.2.</note> and Gods vengeance will more ſpeedily fall upon us, like the rod of an al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond which <hi>Jeremiah</hi> ſaw:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 1.11, 12.</note> for he will haſten his word to performe it; he will take away the hedge, and break downe the wall, and leave us as a prey to our enemies. Now where is that good <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> who laboureth night and day to repaire the breaches of the wall? Where is the man that makes up the hedge,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezech.</hi> 22.30</note> and ſtands in the gap before the Lord for the land, that he
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:176251:33"/>may not deſtroy it? Who is there, like <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that hath power as a Prince, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailes with God for bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings? Who is there, like <hi>Moſes,</hi> that is mighty and potent to hinder Gods pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments from entring in amongſt us? By variance &amp; diſſention we raze downe the wall, and are ſubject to ruine and deſtruction: Oh that we were ſtrongly knit, and firmly joyned under our head corner-ſtone: <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold how good, and how plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant it is for brethren to dwell together in unitie!</hi> Such as ſhall raiſe up the partition wall formerly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moliſhed, and ſhall cauſe difference and oppoſition to grow up, may feare that curſe to fall upon them,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:176251:33"/>which is denounced againſt the builders of Jericho:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joſh.</hi> 6.26.</note> We ought rather to be as a firm and ſure wall, fixed and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveable, ſtanding faſt in the faith, ſupporting and ſtrengthening the weake, reſtoring ſuch as are over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken in a fault,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.1, 2.</note> in the ſpirit of meekneſs, bearing one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>others burthen, reflecting that warmth and influence we receive from above, for the benefit of them that are nigh unto us, to bring them to maturity; and not to be wavering-minded and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable in all our waies, like a bowing wall,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 62.3.</note> and a tottering fence; not to be malicious againſt others,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 10.8.</note> like that hedge which hath a ſerpent hidden in it; not to be fierce and violent in ſharpe inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctives,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:176251:34"/>like a thorne hedge piercing them through with many ſorrowes,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mich.</hi> 7.4.</note> which come nigh unto us. Wicked men are often compared to briers and thornes,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezech.</hi> 2.6.</note> increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and multiplying upon the face of the earth, boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that they can doe miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe.</p>
            <p>Sinue at firſt cumbred the earth with thornes: If <hi>Adam</hi> had abode in his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity, the ground ſhould have been freed from this burthen, &amp; all things ſhould have been common, as they were in the beginning of the Goſpel;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 4.32.</note> neither ſhould any man have ſaid, that ought of the things that he poſſeſſed had been his own. But now the bleſſing is turn'd into a curſe; Yet even
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:176251:34"/>in Gods righteous judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment there is a manifeſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his providence: For ſince by eating the forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den fruit we are corrupted, and that evill root of cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe lies covered in the heart (like <hi>Achans</hi> wedge buried in the earth) and we are ſo farre from that happy communion and overflow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bounty,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joſh.</hi> 7.21.</note>
               <note place="margin">Quam arbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruiſſet, ſub ea legere alium fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num eſſe. <hi>Livi.</hi>
               </note> whereby others might partake with us of thoſe things unto which we have moſt proper right, that we rather (with <hi>Fabius</hi>) thinke it derogates from us, if we plant the tree, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other eate the fruit;
<note place="margin">Et ſua reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere privatae domus, de alienis cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare egregi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am laudem eſſe. <hi>Tacit.</hi>
               </note> Suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing it belongs to private and obſcure men, to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine their owne bounds; but to them of dignity, to encroach upon the territory
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:176251:35"/>and juriſdiction of other men.
<note place="margin">Neque quiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam Ger. manorum proprios ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes habet, ne potentiores humiliores poſſeſsioni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus expel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant. <hi>Caeſar.</hi> Ne familiae rixentur cum vicinis, ac limites ex litibus judicem quaerant. <hi>Varro.</hi>
               </note> Now it pleaſed the Lord, in the beginning of the diſeaſe to ordaine a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy; and when mens de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires were ſo enlarged, that they could not looke upon that which was another mans, as if it had been their owne; but were ready to tranſgreſſe by injurious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſion, Then, to prevent diſcord and enmity, and to ſet limits to our greedy ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite, he did cauſe theſe thornes to ſpring up, which in ſucceeding times might be moſt uſefull and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modious, as well to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the inſatiate avarice of them, who would devoure that which pertaines unto their neighbour; as alſo for the quiet fruition of the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:176251:35"/>portion which is juſtly due unto us:
<note place="margin">Teſtudinem ubi collecta in ſuum te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gimen eſt, tutam ad omnes ictus video eſſe, &amp;c. <hi>Livi.</hi>
               </note> that as the Torteiſe is ſafe, while it keeps within the ſhell, but ſuch parts of it as are put forth become ſubject to harme and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; ſo we be culpable by exceeding the lot that is falne to us, but are free and ſecure containing within our proper bounds. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever then that we ſee theſe thornes, whether in the confines, or adjoyning to the walkes and other di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions of this our plantati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, we may be put in mind of Gods curſe that did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce them.</p>
            <p>And not only by view<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the thornes, but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe by obſerving the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renneſſe of the earth,
<note place="margin">Exoſſatus ager. <hi>Perſius.</hi>
               </note> wherein we are to fixe our
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:176251:36"/>trees, which hath loſt its prime vigour and ſtrength that God gave unto it, to bring forth the tree yeeld<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fruit after his kind: So that no uſefull tree will proſper therein, without much culture, and labour, and coſt; but of it ſelfe it can multiply briers and weeds,
<note place="margin">Nil niſi cum ſpinis gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men habebit ager. <hi>Ovid.</hi>
               </note> which are for the moſt part hurtfull and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judiciall unto us. It was juſt with God, when man did withhold the moſt accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble fruit of obedience from him, and did-bring forth bitter cluſters and grapes of gall,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.32.</note> that the ground ſhould likewiſe detaine its increaſe from ſinfull man, being cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for his ſake, who by his ſinne turn'd Paradiſe into a deſart: And now beholding
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:176251:36"/>the earth (out of which he was taken) rejected of God,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.8.</note> whoſe end is to be burned, he may acknowledge it to be a fit receptacle for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in his death, who for his wickedneſſe deſerves to be rooted out of the land of the living.
<note place="margin">Ac ſaepe vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deas laetam nitentemque arborem, ſi in locum al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terum tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feratur, ſucco terrae dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioris elan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſſe. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crob.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Adam</hi> in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning was a tree of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe planted in a rich and fruitfull ſoile; but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward he was tranſplan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into a deſolate wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, where we his bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches are ſhot forth; and now what good fruit can be expected from us? The ſeed doth partake of the property of that land into which it is tranſported: man is become vaine and unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable; the earth is corrupt and filled with violence:
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:176251:37"/>for all fleſh hath corrupted his way upon the earth.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.11.</note> 
               <hi>Can there any good thing come out of Nazareth?</hi> Can any acceptable fruit ariſe from ſinfull man? Many times we may diſcerne the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſurface of the ground is green and flouriſhing (though ſoone parched in the heat of the yeere) but ſearching into the hidden part,
<note place="margin">Soli ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficies aeſtu facilè ſicca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. <hi>Scal. in Theop.</hi>
               </note> in which the root ſhould bee dilated and ſpread, both for the better eſtabliſhing of the tree,
<note place="margin">Plus alimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti conſequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ex pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fundo, plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta firmius haeret, &amp;c. <hi>Idem.</hi>
               </note> and that the moiſture might from thence be derived un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the uttermoſt boughes, &amp; outmoſt branches, where meeting with the outward warmth, it might be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocted and ordered for the ſtrengthening of the tree,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:176251:37"/>and bringing forth plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant fruit: I ſay, if we digge into that part of the land which is covered, we ſhall ſoon meet with not only a dead, but a killing earth, which cannot afford any good nutriment unto that which is placed therein: E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſuch is the condition of man; There may be an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward forme of godlineſſe, an appearance of religion, ſome ſhew of piety; but let them try and prove them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and inquire into the hidden man, and they ſhall find as much want of deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of earth for this hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly plant of grace, as there was for the good ſeed of the Word;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.5.</note> the ſtony ground reſiſted that, and our hearts of ſtone doe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:176251:38"/>this: Yea, the moſt perfect doe acknowledge that ſinne dwelleth in them, and there is a law in their members,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.</note> warring againſt the law of their mind:
<note place="margin">Tranſlatu facta eſt me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lior, quae noxia quon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam in pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triâ. <hi>Alciat. Pierius.</hi>
               </note> And as that Perſian fruit was poyſon in its owne ſoile, but being removed into an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other country, became ſafe and uſefull; ſo we, abiding in our eſtate of nature, have no good thing dwelling in our fleſh; but being chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and altered by the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Spirit, we may fructifie, and become profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table: yet we ought alwaies to be ſenſible of our corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions remaining within us, which doe encumber our faith, being as a ſtrange and forraine plant, not growing ſo readily, not thriving ſo
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:176251:38"/>ſpeedily as our carnall luſts doe that prevaile againſt us, and overtop this grace with vanities: and being thus op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, we ought to pray unto the Lord (who is able to bring a cleane thing out of an uncleane) to break up the fallow ground of our hearts, putting his law in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our inward parts, that we may beare the image of the Second man, which is heavenly, as we have borne the image of the Firſt man, which is of the earth, ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy: And as at the laſt day we looke for a new earth,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.13.</note> wherein dwelleth righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe; ſo now in this life, having our part in the firſt Reſurrection, we may be enabled to grow in godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and to bring forth
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:176251:39"/>fruit in true holineſſe; and in the end may receive a bleſſing from the Lord, who hath dreſſed us, and gathered the ſtones out of us, taking away that which did oppoſe, and beſtowing all things requiſite for our furtherance in the way of life.</p>
            <p>Thus we have walked into this our Orchard, we have refreſhed our ſelves in our Arbour, we have obſerved the defence thereof, wee have diſcovered the nature and condition of the ſoile; wee ſhould now enter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the trees themſelves: And although there be but a ſmall portion enjoy'd by us of this Land, or brought over to us by the painfull travels and learned workes
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:176251:39"/>of other men, in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of that innumerable and unſpeakable variety, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to the ſight, and good for food, which were pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by God himſelfe in that glorious plantation; yet e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by theſe we now poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe, we may be taught to admire and adore the depth of the riches both of the wiſedome and knowledge of God:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.33.</note> 
               <hi>How unſearchable are his judgements, and his waies paſt finding out!</hi> When one plant finds not learning and art enough to unfold it; but as there is ſome part of it covered in the earth from our ſight, ſo there is ſome property or quality thereof reſerved from our know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: And if we be not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble rightly to diſcerne the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:176251:40"/>uſe of one, then who is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to diſcourſe of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny? Let us in humility con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the truth, and teſtifie againſt our ſelves; How can we deſerve to take delight in the ſweet taſte of any fruit, or to receive comfort and benefit by obſervations collected from any tree, when as our gracious Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the beginning gave us liberty freely to eate of every tree of the garden, yea even of the Tree of life (excepting only the tree of the knowledge of good &amp; evill) and yet we in the height of ingratitude did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell againſt his word? Some have taken paines to ſhew what kind of fruit it was that <hi>Adam</hi> ate; but wee in the ſtate of ignorance can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:176251:40"/>judge of the fruit of the tree of Knowledge: we now know it not; but we feele it, we feele it, even the coare of it ſtill abiding in our hearts; and are juſtly ſcourged out of the garden, never to taſte of theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent fruits, but to eate of the herbe of the field;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.18.</note> Our former plenty being turned into penury, we are joyned in commons with the beaſt. Being falne from the tree to the herbe, from our firſt ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation to this poore eſtate, we might eaſily have been ſuppreſſed and kept downe by the divine juſtice, and for ever have continued void of counſell, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out underſtanding; Or at leaſt if we had been in ſome meaſure enlightened, it
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:176251:41"/>might have been to this end, that wee ſhould bee more apprehenſive of our miſery, and our knowledge ſhould have been as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening of the Syrians eyes,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 6.20.</note> when they were in the midſt of Samaria, to have augmented our feare, being compaſſed about with ſo many enemies; we might then have feared to come nigh unto the tree, leſt it ſhould put us in mind of our diſobedience by ſhunning us,
<note place="margin">Fugiant ut introrſum in fundum ſe reclinent. <hi>Varre.</hi> Arbor pudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinquante homine ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtringit. <hi>Scal. exer.</hi>
               </note> and bending away, as the fruitfull Olive from the Oake; or by cloſing the branches, ſhould ſhut it ſelfe up, that we who are unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy might not taſte of the fruit; or though permitted to approach, yet that the ſhadow thereof ſhould be as
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:176251:41"/>diſaſtrous unto us,
<note place="margin">Qui ſub Sorbo arbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re jacent, rurſus in ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biem ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantur. <hi>Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſtor.</hi>
               </note> as that of the Service tree is reported to be unto ſuch as have bin furious, bringing us to our former weakneſſe; or like the Gourd withering in an inſtant; or like the Apples of Sodome, turning to duſt in the gathering; or elſe turning us to duſt while we eate them, killing by their poyſon; as many fruits have done; the danger whereof hath taught men, in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering of remote parts of the world,
<note place="margin">Sir Richard Hawkins ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervat.</note> not to adventure beyond their knowledge, unleſſe the birds and other creatures doe firſt feed upon them:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.9.</note> But <hi>the Lord will not alwaies chide, neither will he keep his anger for ever: hee hath not dealt with us after our ſinnes, nor rewarded us
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:176251:42"/>according to our iniquities.</hi> For although ſince the fall we are conſtrained to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply our ſcarcity by a more frequent uſe of the herbe than otherwiſe ſhould have been; and the fruit did then degenerate from its primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive perfection,
<note place="margin">Terra poſt lapſum vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioſos fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus proferre coepit: ſed in diluvio major facta eſt mutatio. <hi>Calvin.</hi> Quibus an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtas uda ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis fructus inſipidi <hi>Seal. in Theop.</hi>
               </note> and was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine more impaired, and made much worſe, the earth being corrupted by the floud (a fit remembrance whereof wee may have, when in a wet yeer our fruit becomes unſavoury) ſo that now it is like <hi>Barzillai,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving loſt its former taſte: Yet notwithſtanding God <hi>left not himſelfe without wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 14.17.</note> 
               <hi>in that hee ſtill doth us good</hi> (farre above our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts) <hi>filling our hearts with food and gladneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.15.</note> giving us
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:176251:42"/>ſuch food from the trees as cheares the heart; which may excite us with <hi>David,</hi> to call upon the fruitfull trees to praiſe the Lord, in regard of that vertue that is ſtill remaining in them. The rigour of the firſt ſentence was afterward ſo mitigated, that the Lord by a ſpeciall law doth provide for the preſervation of fruit-trees: When they beſieged a Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 20.6.19.</note> they ſhould not force an axe againſt them (for the tree of the field is mans life.) And alſo hee propounds a reward unto the induſtry of that man which ſhould plant a vineyard, that hee ſhould be diſpenced with, and not goe to the warre, untill hee hath eaten of the fruit of his labour: whereby
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:176251:43"/>he doth encourage all men to be diligent in preparing to bequeath theſe helpfull benefits unto their poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
<note place="margin">Dii me non accipere tantummo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do haec à majoribus voluerunt, ſed etiam poſteris pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere. <hi>Cicere.</hi>
               </note> which they have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from their progeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours. I doe not deny but there may be much offence herein, by ſuch as do whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly addict themſelvs to theſe preſent contentments; it was one of the ſins of Sodome,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 17.28.</note> their great ſecurity and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive delight in planting, whoſe trees were all turned into fewell; wee are fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warned, that the ſame evill will be predominant among us in theſe laſt times: Let us take heed, leſt for want of moderation therein, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come beſtiall, yea worſe than the beaſt, be changed into the trees themſelves,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:176251:43"/>and be without ſenſe or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.21.</note> as he was that planted the vineyard; Wherefore the time being ſhort, wee ſhould uſe the world, as not abuſing it; for the faſhion of this world paſſeth away. If an Heathen,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.31. Quam no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſi &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torridi ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> quam triſtes &amp; ſquallidi trunci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nec. epiſt.</hi>
               </note> upon the ſight of ſome trees which were at firſt planted by himſelfe, and after be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came ſeere and decayed through age, could be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed of his owne mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality; then much more may we by theſe outward helpes be put in mind of our fraile condition here upon earth: And as the Peare-tree (which hath its name from fire) doth grow upward;
<note place="margin">Bacon Cent. Becman de orig.</note> ſo wee in our thoughts and deſires ſhould aſpire unto heavenly bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings.
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:176251:44"/>Man is like a tree tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned upſide downe;
<note place="margin">Homo plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta inverſa.</note> not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee brings forth bad fruit in ſtead of good (though that bee true in moſt) but as the mouth of the tree is in the earth, and from thence drawes its ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getation;
<note place="margin">Ut illinc no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrarum acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onum prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipia hauri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amus. <hi>Scal. exer.</hi>
               </note> ſo our root is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, and from heaven we ſhould derive our power, and the rule of all our acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Chriſt himſelfe is our root, and from him wee ſhould extract grace and ſtrength, that we may bring forth good fruit. Is there ſuch a fulneſſe of power in him, and doe we continue as withered branches, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ſap or nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? Is there ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in him, and doe we ſtill abide in this eſtate of
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:176251:44"/>corruption? <hi>Adam</hi> was ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed out of Eden, and we ſhall never be admitted to come nigh unto the tree of life here upon earth, to find any permanent joy, any ſettled aſſurance of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment here in this world. If we ſeeke for any conſtant felicity here, our labour will be in vaine: Our Tree of life is in heaven,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Revel.</hi> 22.</note> and from Chriſt alone we muſt receive all bleſſings, whereof we ſtand in need. Without him we can doe nothing; but we can doe all things through Chriſt, which ſtrengtheneth us: In our ſelves we are as wild olive branches by our fall cut off from that life, which at firſt was given unto us; Now there is no other
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:176251:45"/>meanes whereby to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve us from deſtruction, but only by being graffed into that good Olive tree,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.</note> who left his fatneſſe, not to bee promoted over the trees, but to be humbled and abaſed, that he might exalt us unto glory: There was an <hi>Inciſion</hi> into him, that there might be an <hi>Inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of us; His ſide was ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that we might enter in, and with <hi>Thomas</hi> apprehend him for our comfort and ſalvation. If the touch of the garment drew vertue from him for the curing of the body, then our laying hold upon him, and applying him to our ſelves, will cure our ſoules: Wee muſt not be in Chriſt as a dead branch is in a tree, onely
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:176251:45"/>cleaving to the body of it for a time (reſembling for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall profeſſours in the Church, without the life of grace) but by reall partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of that heavenly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence, when wee are ſtrongly knit unto him, and there is an union between him and us: When my Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved is mine, and I am his; when we abide in him,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 15.4.</note> and he in us; he receiving us by love, we applying him by faith, and extracting grace and holineſſe out of him,
<note place="margin">Ut coale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcant eſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſponſus mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuus, ſuppe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditantis ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boris, hauri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entis ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culi. <hi>Scal. in Theop.</hi> Quo turgent tempore plantae ad germinatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, rectè inſeri. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </note> as the cyon ſucks the nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from the ſtocke; this yeelding, and offering, and ſupplying; the other draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and receiving. We make choice to graffe in the Spring, when the ſap doth riſe, that there may be moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:176251:46"/>to nouriſh the cyons; ſo we ſhould ſeek for Gods bleſſing upon us in his ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, at which time he is moſt ready to extend the armes of his mercy towards us. It is ſaid in Saint <hi>Luke, The power of the Lord was preſent to heale them:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 5.17.</note> Not that his might was at any time defective or dimini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, but it did now ſhine forth more gloriouſly in his willingneſſe to conferre his favours upon them that came unto him; ſo in the uſe of his Word and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, he doth moſt fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently lift up the light of his countenance upon us, opening and bringing forth his treaſures, whereby wee may be enriched. After we have fixed the cyons, wee
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:176251:46"/>doe apply ſome clay,
<note place="margin">Lutum adhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beri, ut ne reficcentur. <hi>Scal. in Theop.</hi>
               </note> or the like, to prevent the drineſſe by reaſon of the wound, and to help to faſten it; wherein we may conſider, that ſubſtance whereof we were framed, which was red earth,
<note place="margin">Nos argillam primum ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim apponi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </note> as ſome conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture from the ſignification of <hi>Adams</hi> name; being like the potters clay, which is commended as moſt fitting for our preſent uſe. Where the Lord ſpeaketh by the Prophet,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 18.6.</note> that we are in his hand as clay in the hand of the potter, it is added in the following Verſes,
<note place="margin">Inutileſque falce ramos amputans, foeliciores inſerit. <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat.</hi>
               </note> that hee will plucke up that Nation and Kingdome which doth evill in his ſight; and he will plant that Nation &amp; King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome which turne from their evill: This gives us juſt
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:176251:47"/>occaſion to magnifie the Name of the Lord, who ſuffering others to continue in the eſtate of nature, as wild olives (and ſuch were we of this Land in former time, aliens from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth of Iſrael, ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers from the Covenants of promiſe, having no hope, and without God in the world) Yea, which addeth to the riches of his mercy and love, hath broken off the naturall branches, and hath graffed us in, that we might partake of the root and fatneſſe of the Olive: Then let us receive the grace that is offered, and not count our ſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of ſo great ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. We know that every graft that is put into the
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:176251:47"/>ſtocke doth not grow; there may be two at the ſame time, whereof the one doth proſper, and the other is dried up; like two men in one bed, the one taken,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 17.34.</note> the other left: They are not all Iſrael, that are of Iſrael; they are not all endued with the Spirit from above, and with ſaving gifts, who aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the name of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and are incorporated into the viſible Church: There is an indiſpoſition in many men, which makes them uncapable of the grace that is propounded unto them. When wee take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of the tenderneſſe of the graft in the beginning, how apt it is to be broken off by any caſualty, we may ponder our owne weakneſſe
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:176251:48"/>and frailty, how ſoone we may be ſhaken, having no ſufficiency in our ſelves; and therefore it was a neceſſary caveat, which the Apoſtle gives to them newly graf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed in,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.</note> 
               <hi>Be not high-minded, but feare; Thou beareſt not the root, but the root thee:</hi> We ſtand not by our owne power, but by faith in Chriſt. Being thus feeble at the firſt, wee muſt imitate the trees in growing, who caſe not untill they obtaine perfect ſtrength, and be ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and fortified againſt the violent rage of the wind, and hardened with the cover of the barke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all oppoſition, and advanced by the height of the branches above the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of enemies; ſo wee
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:176251:48"/>ſhould be <hi>ſtrong in the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.</note> 
               <hi>and in the power of his might, that we may be able to withſtand in the evill day, and having done all to ſtand.</hi> Wee ſee how flexible a young tree or a branch is, that wee can bend it, and make it grow which way wee will; ſo ſhould wee be tractable, and governed by the rule of the Word, never reſiſting the good will of the Almighty God, leſt he puniſh us, as hee did the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites which were his Vine that he brought out of Egypt, intending to plant them in a fruitfull land: but when they walked ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bornly before him, and would not be ruled by him, nor obſerve his ſtatutes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a ſtiffe-necked people,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:176251:49"/>he then ſubdued them, and led them which way hee pleaſed, making them bend untill they did breake, and fall in the wilderneſſe: As for the tender branches which were lately ſprung up, being more humble and obedient, he cauſed them to take deep root, and fill the land. In viewing the young trees that ſtand divers yeeres, and require much labour and diligence in watering, and ſupporting, and preſerving them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they bring forth fruit, wee may call to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance the time of our childhood &amp; youth, which were vanity, when wee ſpake as children, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood as children, thought as children, bringing forth
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:176251:49"/>no fruit, or if any, no better than wild grapes, walking according to the courſe of this world, having our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation among the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of diſobedience: So that the Lord might juſtly have left us unto our ſelves,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.31.</note> that wee ſhould have eaten of the fruit of our owne way, and been filled with our owne devices. Let not us deſpiſe the riches of his goodneſſe, and long-ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and forbearance, which ſhould bring us to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: He hath permitted us to ſtand three yeers,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 13.</note> like the figge-tree in the Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, ſeeking fruit upon us, and hath found none: Hee in mercy addes a fourth yeere, that we may in ſome meaſure recompence his
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:176251:50"/>coſt, and ſatisfie his expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation. The time paſt of our life may ſuffice us to have walked in laſciviouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, when we were foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, diſobedient, deceived, ſerving divers luſts and pleaſures; but now let us no longer live to the luſts of men, but to the will of God, and bring forth the fruit of the Spirit. It is time to awake out of ſleep; the winter is paſt, the raine is over and gone: The branch of the figge-tree is tender, and putteth forth greene figges, the vines with the tender grape give a good ſmell, the almond tree doth flouriſh, the flowers appeare on the earth; The ſpring of our youth is farre ſpent, the ſummer of our
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:176251:50"/>perfect ſtrength is at hand:
<note place="margin">Verba ſunt folia, fructus quaeritur.</note> The green leaves of good words are not ſufficient; wee muſt bloſſome as the Roſe in our good purpoſes. Can we looke for fruit up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe trees in ſummer, that have no bloſſomes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them in the ſpring? Can wee expect an increaſe of grace and holineſſe in the ripe age of them, who have not ſo much as the hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full bloſſomes of godly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions and pious endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours in their younger yeeres? This is impoſſible with man, but with God all things are poſſble. Bloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomes alone are not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent; for ſuch as proceed not beyond faire promiſes and laudable beginnings, are like unto that Cherry-tree that
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:176251:51"/>hath double bloſſomes,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The</hi> Flori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pondio, &amp;c. <hi>Purchas.</hi> Statim à ſubeunte fructu pelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur flos, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que abole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. <hi>Scal. in Theop.</hi>
               </note> but never yeelds any fruit: Or like ſome trees in America, that beare flowers at all times, but no fruit at any time. Wee know the fruit increaſing doth thruſt off the bloſſome that did for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly incloſe it; ſo wee ſhould not reſt in ſhort eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaies or weake attempts, but goe on to abſolute perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance.
<note place="margin">A longitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine digi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tali dactyli appellati ſunt. <hi>Perot.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>David</hi> ſaith, The righteous man ſhall flouriſh like the Palme-tree; whoſe fruit doth grow like fingers, and are thereof named. The workes of our hands, the actions of our lives, are of the fruit of righteouſneſſe, that doth juſtifie our faith, and is acceptable in the ſight of God. Thinke not to pleaſe the Lord with thy
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:176251:51"/>cold devotions in old age, with thy ſorry repentance in the latter end: Hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires the firſt fruits, and doeſt thou thinke to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, when thy ſummer fruits are gathered, thy daies are ſpent in vanity, and thy ſervice and obedience is no better than the grape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gleaning after the vintage, two or three olive berries after the ſhaking, or the figs ſo bad they could not bee eaten? ſuch may forſake their owne mercy while they beleeve lying vanities, and expect a long continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance here upon earth. It is true, God promiſeth his people, that their daies ſhall be as the daies of a tree,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.22.</note> in regard of their ſtrength and duration; and when they
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:176251:52"/>reſt from their labour, they are tranſplanted into Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe: But let no impenitent ſinner deceive himſelfe, and proceed in his wickedneſſe; rather let him conſider his frailty, by obſerving that the young tree dyes as well as the old;
<note place="margin">Poma ſi cruda ſunt vi avellun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, &amp;c. <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cero de Sen.</hi>
               </note> and as the ripe fruit falls off, ſo the green is plucked off by force: In like manner, one dyeth in his old age,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi> 21.23. &amp; 24.20. &amp; 9.17.</note> another in his full ſtrength, being wholly at eaſe and quiet; his breaſts are full of milke, and his bones are moiſtened with marrow. Wickedneſſe ſhall be broken as a tree, even ſuddenly confounded, and overthrowne as with a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt; like that flouriſhing Olive (deſcribed by the
<note n="*" place="margin">Qualem ſi quis aquis, &amp; fertilis ube<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re terrae educat, cùm ſubito immiſsis praeceps Aquilonia nimbis: Venit hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ems, nigrâ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que evulſam tendit hare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nâ. <hi>Val. Flac. lib.</hi> 6.</note> Poet, and may well be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:176251:52"/>unto himſelfe, whoſe untimely death prevented the conſummation of his worke) which was planted in a fertile ſoile, and wate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with much diligence, and afterward was plucked up by the roots by a violent North-wind, before it had yeelded any fruit:
<note place="margin">Ingenium foelix, immaturâ morte pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventus. <hi>Seal. Poet.</hi>
               </note> Even ſo many ſtrong men, who are accommodated with all things requiſite for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of their lives; yet God doth weaken their ſtrength in the way, &amp; take them away in the midſt of their daies.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi> 15.32.</note> Vanity ſhall be the recompence of them that truſt therein: He ſhall be cut off <hi>before his time, and his branch ſhall not be green: He ſhall ſhake off his unripe grape as the Vine, and
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:176251:53"/>ſhall caſt off his flower as the Olive:</hi> Wherefore be not mocked, as if thou ſhouldeſt not be moved, when thy foundation is placed upon ſo weake a ſubſtance; but rather prepare for thy death: for in a moment thou maiſt goe to the grave, and lye downe in the duſt. And if the tree fall towards the South, or towards the North, in the place where the tree falleth there it ſhall lye: If thou haſt inclined to the Sunne of Righteouſnes, and haſt extended thy branches in ſeeking for the beames of his mercy, and the influence of his grace to refreſh thy ſoule, that thou mighteſt be enabled to bring forth good fruit; then thou ſhalt have comfort in
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:176251:53"/>the end: but if thou haſt withdrawne thy ſelfe from the light of Gods counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and art beſt pleaſed in the darke ſhade of reſt and eaſe, never ſeeking for heavenly bleſſings, then great will be thy fall. How can any man thinke for a long time to eſcape unpuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 15.2.</note> when God doth take away every branch, and hew downe every tree that beareth not fruit?
<note place="margin">Infoecundas vivere diu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiùs. <hi>Scal. in Ariſt.</hi> Quae colun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur arbores celeriùs ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſcere: co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gimus eas multum o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peris facere. <hi>Idem in Theop. See Biſhop Juels life. Doctor Rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nolds, and Maſter Bol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons life.</hi>
               </note> And yet if the Lord ſhould deferre his ſpeedy execution of judgement againſt thine e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill workes (as it is noted, that the barren trees live longeſt, and the moſt fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full conſume themſelves by much bearing, repreſenting thoſe holy men, which have waſted their ſtrength
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:176251:54"/>by their godly labours;) yet notwithſtanding if thou doſt perſiſt in impiety, thou ſhalt not be acquitted,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi> 21.30.</note> but art reſerved to the day of deſtruction:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 8.12.</note> 
               <hi>Though a ſinner doe evill an hundred times, and his dayes be prolonged, yet it ſhall not bee well with him, neither ſhall he prolong his daies, which are as a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, becauſe hee feareth not before God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Quid tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ignoras magnas diu creſcere, unâ horâ extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Q Curt.</hi>
               </note> The tree which hath been many yeeres growing up, may bee caſt downe in an inſtant: Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though thou haſt been ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for a long time, yet ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance may ſuddenly over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take thee; wherefore let my counſell be acceptable unto thee,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.27.</note> and <hi>breake off thy ſins by righteouſneſſe, and thine iniquities by ſhewing mercy
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:176251:54"/>to the poore, if it may bee a lengthening of thy tranquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</hi> The longer thou con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinueſt in thy ſinnes, the ſtronger are the cords of vanity; thy nature is cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt of it ſelfe, being as a law in thy members, and an inveterate cuſtome of doing evill is as a ſecond nature, and both doe warre againſt the Law of God. The young plant that hath been ſet but a ſhort time, may be plucked up with ſmall la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, whereas that which hath been fixed divers yeeres, cannot be removed without much difficulty: If thy corruptions be firmly rooted by ancient reſidence within thee, how canſt thou get the dominion over them? How wilt thou be
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:176251:55"/>able to prevaile againſt them? There is no meanes under heaven, whereby thou canſt hope for delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, but only by the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and love of God: Then pray unto him to have mercy upon thee, and to make thee the branch of his planting, the worke of his hands, that hee may be glorified. Our help ſtandeth in the Name of the Lord; It is hee that doth cauſe Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael to bloſſome and bud,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 27.6.</note> and fill the face of the world with fruit. If we had not the dew of heaven, we ſhould not have the fatneſſe of the earth: If we had not the comfortable heat of the ſunne, we ſhould not have the fruit of the trees: with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the grace of God, there
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:176251:55"/>can neither be beginning nor increaſe of ſpirituall bleſſings. The bud of a good deſire, the bloſſome of a pious reſolution, the fruit of a vertuous action proceeds from the Lord; the readineſſe to will, the power to performe is the gift of God, and doth come from the Father of lights: All our labour is in vaine, except the Lord gives his bleſſing; It is vaine to riſe up early, to ſit up late, to ſpend the whole day in dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, and planting, and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering, unleſſe that he doth cauſe the worke of our hands to proſper. Now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſenſible of this our infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, that we can doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of our ſelves, wee ought to bee the more
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:176251:56"/>thankfull, in remembring the benefits that we have received from the good will of the Almighty God, who hath not left us deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of any meet helpe, whereby we may be fitted to bring forth good fruit.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40.5.</note> 
               <hi>Many, O Lord my God, are thy wonderfull workes which thou haſt done, and thy thoughts which are to us<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward: they cannot be recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned up in order unto thee: If I would declare and ſpeake of them, they are moe than can be numbred.</hi> There are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers things required to make the plants ſprout, and yeeld their increaſe; as the kindneſſe and fertility of the ground: and hath not God enriched us with his bleſſings, and refreſhed us
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:176251:56"/>with his mercies? The dropping of the aire: and hath he not ſent his Word, as a ſweet ſhowre, to ſatisfie our thirſty ſoules? The changes and ſeaſons of the yeere: and hath he not gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven us a Winter,
<note place="margin">Feigus &amp; cohibet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus calorem, &amp; corrobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat. <hi>Scal. in Theop.</hi>
               </note> wherein to gather ſtrength, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare for future time; and a Summer, wherein to ſhew forth his goodneſſe, and to produce good fruit? The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of the Sunne: and hath not the Sun of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe ſhined clearly unto us, and ſeemed to be even fixed in this our He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſphere? How few bee there that can remember the bright and chearfull morning of this glorious day? I pray God to make this one day as a thouſand
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:176251:57"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:176251:57"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:176251:58"/>yeeres, that never any may ſee the end of this time, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the end of all things come, when time ſhall be no more: Having ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly enjoyed ſuch excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent bleſſings,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sands trav.</hi> Laetiſsimae arberes at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que fertiliſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimae. Non fit con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariorum viciſsitudo, nihil obtun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, eſt aequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitas. <hi>Scal. in Theop.</hi>
               </note> let us be fruitfull. In Egypt many of the trees beare fruit, and moſt of them their leaves all the yeere, in regard there is no contrariety in the aire; but alwaies an equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, that doth promote and further the trees in their bearing. Now wee having unceſſantly the happy fruiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all good meanes that may be helpfull unto us, ought to abound more and more in good workes, and to walk worthy of ſo great love. What could the Lord have done for us that hee
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:176251:58"/>hath not done? We have been planted as a tree by the waters,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.8.</note> and that ſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth out her roots by the river, and ſeeth not when heat commeth, but her leafe is green; and ſhe is not care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in the yeer of drought, nor ceaſeth from yeelding fruit. And as the tree is pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and many of the boughes cut off, that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidue may be more fruitfull; ſo the Lord hath corrected and rebuked us, that wee might be free from ſecurity, and learne to amend our lives, and walke in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.19.</note> 
               <hi>Hee doth chaſten as many as hee loveth, and ſcourgeth every ſonne whom he receiveth;</hi> which is as the ſprinkling on of ſalt, to keep us from corruption. The
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:176251:59"/>trees of the field are little regarded,
<note place="margin">Planta ferax falcem pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, petitque frequentem. Putationes redinte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grant, &amp; ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventam affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runc. <hi>Scal. in Theop.</hi>
               </note> but thoſe of the garden are often look't un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to and repaired. In exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of us, God dealeth with us as with ſonnes, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting us in judgement for our reformation, not conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming us in fury to our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. A plant cut un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonably dyeth; but cut in due time, it proſpers the better. The times and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are in Gods hands: he doth then purge his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, when it may be moſt for their diſcipline and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment; that our old er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours and infirmities may paſſe away, and we being regenerated may walke in newneſſe of life; as in pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the withered and dry branches are taken away,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:176251:59"/>and young twigs doe ſhoot forth, that may be fruitfull: Let us never forget Gods dealing with us, when hee did ſtretch out his hand,
<note place="margin">Anno 1625.</note> and did threaten to deſtroy the tree with the fruit thereof, and to cut off branch and ruſh in one day by the noi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome peſtilence, lopping off many ten thouſands, and leaving the chiefe body of the tree naked and bare; yet then he preſerved us in ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: we were delivered from the mouth of that Lion, and we are ſtill defended by the ſhield of his favour, that we may glorifie his Name by a godly converſation. Will not all this move us to return unto the Lord? His bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits conferred, his fatherly reprehenſion, his protecting
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:176251:60"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:176251:60"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:176251:61"/>us by his providence, when he ſeverely puniſhed others? Behold, I have ſet before you life and death; I have declared Gods mercy to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us, and his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon others; Now what tribute or offering doth the Lord require of us, but only the fruit of our thoughts, in meditation up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his word and works; the fruit of our lips, in ſhewing forth his praiſe; and the fruit of our lives, in ſerving him acceptably, with reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and godly feare? We all profeſſe that wee are branches of that Root,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.17. &amp; 12.33.</note> Chriſt Jeſus: Now every good tree brings forth good fruit, and a corrupt tree e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill fruit; for by their fruit ye ſhall know them: Can a
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:176251:61"/>fig-tree beare olive berries,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 3.12.</note> or a vine figs? If the root be holy, ſo are the branches: If wee bee members of Chriſt,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.16.</note> wee muſt doe the workes of our heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Doe wee deſire that every tree in our ground ſhould be fruitfull, and yet will we our ſelves be bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren? As ſome parents would have their children walke in a good way, yet they themſelves will runne into exceſſe of riot; Shall others be excited by the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine bleſſings, and power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full meanes that they have enjoyed, to bring forth the good fruit of obedience? and wilt thou, who haſt been a partaker of the ſame bleſſings, bring forth impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and rebellion? As the
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:176251:62"/>influence of the ſame Sunne ripeneth the ſweet grape, and the ſowre crab; but ſuch wild trees are not ſuffered long to continue in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe of the Church: Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry plant which my Father hath not planted ſhall be rooted up; only the fruitfull trees ſhall be ſupported and ſtrengthened; Being planted in that garden, in the midſt whereof is the Tree of life, which doth diſtribute of its grace and vertue unto all the trees that are round about it: Of Chriſts fulneſſe have all we received, and grace for grace.
<note place="margin">Ulmus &amp; vitis, Ruta &amp; ficus.</note> It is obſerved what a ſympathie there is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the trees, how divers of them proſper beſt, when they have ſuch and ſuch ſtand nigh unto them; and
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:176251:62"/>ſome of them will never beare,
<note place="margin">Exciſo mare palmite, ſterileſcit foemina. <hi>Perottus. Sands trav.</hi>
               </note> This we know aſſuredly, that we can doe no good thing, unleſſe we have our ability from Chriſt, who is that tree which is deſcribed to beare twelve manner of fruits, and to yeeld the fruit every moneth:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.2.</note> As he is ſo in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe full of grace and truth, evermore doing good unto us, and beſtowing all kinds of bleſſings upon us; ſo he gives power to us, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him, to become the ſonnes of God, enabling us in ſome meaſure to bring forth not one, or ſome few kinds, but divers and ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry fruits. The Apoſtle, when hee ſpeakes of the fruit of the Spirit, hee na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:176251:63"/>love, and joy, and peace: then he addes, long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuffering and gentleneſſe; and yet theſe are not all: for he annexeth goodneſſe, faith,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.22.</note> meekneſſe, tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. And elſewhere ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing the fruit of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, hee mentioneth righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe and truth. He that delights in planting,
<note place="margin">Dapibus menſas one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabat in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emptis, Primus vere rooſam, atque autumno carpere po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma. <hi>Virg.</hi>
               </note> will not be ſatisfied with ſome few ſorts of fruit, and in being provided for a ſhort time, or a part of the yeer; but will be deſirous of the beſt choice and varietie that may be; and to have ſuch fruit as may be uſefull, during the whole yeere: Some that may bee ripe with the ſooneſt, and other that may endure a long time; taking ſpeciall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:176251:63"/>in that which is moſt durable, that he may be provided when others are deſtitute. Oh that wee were wiſe for the good of our ſoules! wee would be more delighted in ſeeking for graces, that wee might be perfect, and thorowly furniſhed unto every good worke, than any man can bee in theſe outward con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentments; and with an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly emulation wee would be more covetous of the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall gifts, wherewith o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are adorned, than e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Ahab</hi> was of <hi>Naboths</hi> vineyard.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 21.</note> What diligence would wee give to <hi>adde to our faith, vertue;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5.</note> 
               <hi>and to ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, knowledge; and to know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, temperance; and to temperance, patience; and to
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:176251:64"/>patience, godlineſſe; and to godlineſſe, brotherly kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; and to brotherly kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, charity; for if theſe be in us, and abound, wee ſhould not be</hi> Barren <hi>nor</hi> Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitfull <hi>in the knowledge of our Lord Jeſus Christ:</hi> Wherefore, when wee ſee the Almond tree of any man to bloſſome betimes, and to promiſe a plenteous increaſe; when wee ſee a young man cleanſing his way, by taking heed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto according to Gods word, let us alſo bee there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by provoked to redeem the time, and to remember our Creatour in the daies of our youth. When wee ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve another mans Vine to bee laden with goodly cluſters; when we take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:176251:64"/>of a man who doth good, and rejoyceth in the workes of his hands (as <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> ſpeaks) let us alſo be excited to labour for that gladneſſe in our hearts,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 3.12.22.</note> which is better than the increaſe of come and wine.
<note place="margin">Morus quafi <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, per Antiph. Serior at Morus, nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam mſi frigore lapſo Germinat, &amp; ſapiens no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mina falſa gerat <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciat. Pſal.</hi> 74.47. <hi>For</hi> Mulber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, <hi>now it is</hi> Sycomores.</note> When wee view the Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berry tree of another man to forbeare ſending forth any buds, untill the danger of froſts be paſt; when we conſider how ſuch a man doth wiſely decline what may prevent or hinder his bringing good fruit unto perfection, let us be ſtirred up to aske wiſedome of God (who giveth liberally) that we may avoid the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety of ſuch as are congea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in their ſinnes, and their hearts frozen as hard as
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:176251:65"/>ſtones; by meanes whereof our good deſires may bee nipt in the bud, and we may bee occaſioned to caſt our fruit before the time: It had been as good not to have begun, as not to continue untill the appointed time.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 92.14.</note> 
               <hi>Thoſe that be planted in the houſe of the Lord, ſhall flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh in the courts of our God: they ſhall ſtill bring forth fruit in old age; they ſhall be fat and flouriſhing.</hi> Though other trees be ſeere, and full of moſſe when they are old, and beare leſſe than formerly; yet the trees of Righteouſnes muſt abound more and more, growing unto perfection and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Chriſt is come, that we might have life, and might have it more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly.
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:176251:65"/>A true beleever ought alwaies to grow in ſtrength, and to beare good fruit, that hee might bee found doing the will of his Maſter. Wee muſt not bee like the haſty fruit before the Summer, which when hee that looketh upon it ſeeth it,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa</hi> 28.4.</note> while it is yet in his hand, he eateth it up; Wee muſt never deſiſt from the performance of holy duties. Chriſt curſed the fig-tree, upon which hee found no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but leaves: But why ſhould that tree be dried up from the roots, when the time of figges was not yet?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mar.</hi> 11.13.</note> Thereby he taught his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, that they muſt conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually bring forth fruit: Let not the young man ſay, the time of bearing is not yet
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:176251:66"/>come: Let not the old man ſay, the time is now paſt, leſt both of them bee bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted by the vengeance of God, who is a conſuming fire. If wee be graffed in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong others, and partake of the root, wee muſt ſhew it forth by a fruitfull conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation. The Word doth quicken us; and where there is life, it will appeare. If God doth not forſake the gray-headed, nor caſt us off in the time of old age, then wee alſo ſhould not ceaſe, while wee live to praiſe the Lord,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 146.2.</note> and to ſing praiſes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our God, while we have any being. That we may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the more ſtrength and vertue, whereby wee may be enabled to perſevere un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the end, we muſt labour
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:176251:66"/>for humility.
<note place="margin">Excelſae ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bores fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum puſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum ferunt. <hi>Scal. in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt.</hi>
               </note> The lofty trees are not onely expoſed to the raging ſtormes, but alſo the fruit they beare is ſmall. It is obſerved,
<note place="margin">Bacon Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</note> the lowneſſe of the bough ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the fruit greater, and to ripen better, becauſe it doth participate of the root more effectually than other branches can doe, that are more remote: <hi>God reſiſteth the proud, but hee giveth grace to the humble.</hi> Such as have learned of Chriſt to bee lowly, ſhall bee filled with good things, whereas the rich ſhall be ſent empty away. As wee are to beare fruit at all times, without fainting or being weary in well-doing; ſo we muſt be fruitfull in every part of us. There is a fabulous report
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:176251:67"/>concerning our ſpice, that it ſhould all proceed from one tree, and one kind is the root, and another is the barke, and a third is the fruit, which is folded up in a fourth, &amp;c. though this be not true in it ſelfe, yet it is ſignificant to ſet before us a faithfull Chriſtian, who ſeekes to glorifie God in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very power and faculty, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering up himſelf as a ſweet odour, preſenting his body as a living ſacrifice,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.1.</note> holy, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to God, which is his reaſonable ſervice: As there is no member of Chriſt that is not lively and operative, ſo there is no part of a Chriſtian that ſhould not bee exerciſed as an inſtrument of praiſe and thankſgiving unto God.
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:176251:67"/>Some plants wee have in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimation,
<note place="margin">Glycyrrhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za.</note> in regard of the root only, that is very help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full unto us: Others are maintained in regard of the commodious uſe of the leaves.
<note place="margin">Alba morus: Eſt bicolor morus, bom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byx veſcetur uträque. <hi>Vida.</hi>
               </note> Some trees doe powre out a pleaſing li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor out of the body,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The</hi> Palme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>tree. Herberts trav. They bore the barkes full of holes &amp;c. Sands trav.</hi>
               </note> which doth refreſh the weary traveller; Others have their fruit growing out of the bole and branches, as moſt of them in Egypt. We ſhould not be like any one, but all of theſe in our abundant fruitfulneſſe; and ſhould be filled and adorned with all the gifts and graces of the Spirit: And as every part was created by the power, and is ſupported and nouriſhed by the favour of God; ſo it ſhould returne
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:176251:68"/>ſome fruit of thankſgiving and obedience: for there is a ſchiſme in the body of that man, when the ſame member brings forth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary fruits; as for the tongue to bleſſe God,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>James</hi> 3.</note> and curſe men; or when one part ſeems to beare good fruit, as in lifting up the hands to God in praier; And another part beares grapes of gall, when the feet are ſwift to ſhed bloud. We may obſerve how <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> who compares him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to a greene Olive tree in the houſe of God,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 52.8.</note> was fruitfull in every branch: He did conſider that it was God who planted him at firſt,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.13.</note> who made him fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and wonderfully, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering him in his mothers
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:176251:68"/>wombe, whoſe eyes did ſee his ſubſtance, and in whoſe booke all his members were written, which in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance were faſhioned. And as hee doth acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that he received his beginning from God; ſo he deſires, that both the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and the outward man may bee devoted to Gods ſervice: hee ſtirres up his ſoule,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.1.</note> and all that was with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in him to bleſſe the Lord.
<note place="margin">&amp; 40.8.</note> The law was within his heart;
<note place="margin">&amp; 16.7.</note> His reines did inſtruct him in the night ſeaſon;
<note place="margin">&amp; 35.10.</note> All his bones did ſay, Lord, who is like unto thee? He was purpoſed,
<note place="margin">&amp; 17.3.</note> that his mouth ſhould not tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe;
<note place="margin">&amp; 25.15.</note> His eyes were ever towards the Lord; He did encline his eare to a Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble:
<note place="margin">&amp; 49.4.</note>
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:176251:69"/>he waſht his hands in innocencie.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 26.6.</note> God gave him ſtrength in his armes, and kept his feet from ſlipping. In like manner, we, hoping to be glorified in the whole ſpirituall body, ſhould praiſe God in every part of our mortall body: <hi>O come let us fall downe, and kneele before the Lord our Maker;</hi> let us goe to the houſe of God; let our eyes wait upon the Lord; let us joyne our hands, and lift them up in prayer, thereby remembring to pray for other members that are united unto the ſame body.</p>
            <p>Again, let us divide them, that one may not know what the other doth, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend them in giving with ſimplicity,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.8.</note> doing good to
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:176251:69"/>all, even to them on the left hand, though with more fulneſſe and alacrity to them on the right hand, the houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold of faith. Let our tongue be our glory in praiſing God. And as the leaves of the tree of life were for the healing of the Nations, ſo let our words be ſeaſoned and tempered with wiſdome and love, that they may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme what is evill, and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter grace unto the hearers. As there is ſome ſimilitude in the ſhape and proportion of the tongue,
<note place="margin">Fert folium linguae, fert poma fimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma cordi. <hi>De Perſico pomo in Alciato.</hi>
               </note> and of the leaves of divers trees, as alſo of very many herbs, (which therefore have their names given them from that part) ſo there is ſome reſemblance betweene them. For as we can diſcerne what tree it is
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:176251:70"/>that we behold, by the leafe, although there be no fruit remaining upon it at that time; ſo we can under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the diſpoſition of the heart by the words of the mouth: for <hi>out of the aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of the heart the mouth ſpeaketh.</hi> Yet becauſe the tongue is a world of iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and an unruly evill, we can diſtinguiſh more perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by workes than words. As in the parable of the two Sonnes, the firſt ſaid, he would not go into the Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, but afterward he went; the ſecond ſaid, I goe, Sir, and went not: the younger did bear the broader leaves,
<note place="margin">Mat. 21.29.</note> but the elder had the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieſt fruit. Words are ſoone uttered, and many times raſhly ſpoken, like the leaves
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:176251:70"/>that in a ſhort time come to their utmoſt extent: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the fruit of action is more deliberate, and requires much ſpace and leiſure to bring it to perfect maturity. Although we ſhould, for want of that bridle which <hi>David</hi> ſpeakes of,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39.1.</note> ſin with our tongue,
<note place="margin">Junipero ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na pro folio eſt. <hi>Plin. Soc.</hi>
               </note> and our words be like the leaves of the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niper, ſharp and piercing as a thorne; yet let not our deeds be like the fruit of the Pine,
<note place="margin">Cadentibus ex alto f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctibus, ſi fortè feriatur, ſaepe interficitur, &amp;c. <hi>Imag. deor.</hi>
               </note> wounding or killing ſuch as are under them when they fall: Let not our anger by lying longin our hearts be as the kernell and ſeed of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, which will grow up in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to deadly hatred. Where there is a faire promiſe of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment and reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, there may be ſome for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance.
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:176251:71"/>The fig-tree was ſpared for a time,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 13.7.</note> in regard it was green and flouriſhing; whereas if it had beene wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, it ſhould have beene cut downe in the firſt yeere, and not ſuffered untill the fourth.
<note place="margin">Uvae contra vehementiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fimum ſolis ardorem mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niantur. <hi>Kec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker.</hi> Et contra pluviam et frigus. <hi>Id.</hi>
               </note> A gentle anſwer pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifieth wrath, even as the leaves protect the fruit from the burning heat of the ſun; and as they cheriſh and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend it againſt ſtormes when it is young and tender, ſo the truth of our word, whereby we are engaged, ſhould be a ſtrong motive to produce the reall and abſolute per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance: Otherwiſe if we have a torrent of words, and no actuall diſcharge of our fidelity; if the ſhowers of our deeds be not in ſome ſort anſwerable to the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:176251:71"/>thunder of our voice, we may be likened to that Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an fig-tree,
<note place="margin">Peltae effigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>em habet, fructum inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gens creſcere prohibiet. <hi>Sca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>exer.</hi>
               </note> the leafe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is as large as a buckler, and the fruit no bigger than a beane. The conſideration of our weake condition may occaſion us to bring forth that in our lives, which was formerly conceived in our hearts, and is come to the birth in our words. While we have opportunity let us doe good: The time is ſhort, the faſhion of this world paſſeth away:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 64.6.</note> We all doe fade as a leafe, and our ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities like the wind have taken us away.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi> 13.25.</note> 
               <hi>Job</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pareth himſelfe to a leafe driven to and fro. Such is our feeble eſtate here upon earth; if God doth blow upon us, we are ſcattered;
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:176251:72"/>if nipt with the froſt of ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<note place="margin">Quam mult in ſylvis, au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tumni frigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re primo, lapfa cadunt folia. <hi>Virg l.</hi> 6. Ut nunc ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae frigora brumae nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent ſylvas. <hi>Sen. Hippol.</hi>
               </note> or waſted with the winter of age, we fall to the ground; and yet how few there be that doe remember their latterend! but rather, in the fall of the leafe, they hope for new ſtrength, and perfect recovery of former health, and never thinke of the fall of the tree it ſelfe, that before this winter be ended thou maiſt be brought downe to the pit. The Lord give us wiſdome to lay this to heart, and to wait for our appointed change. In the concluſion of the yeere be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold thine own diſſolution; in the budding of the ſpring,
<note place="margin">Terra viret rutilantque ſuis poma au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea ramis. <hi>Bal Caſtil.</hi> Redit ecce anni melio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris origo. <hi>Sincerus.</hi>
               </note> when the trees begin to be apparelled with a freſh beauty, when the branches that lately ſeemed to be
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:176251:72"/>dead are again covered with their leaves, and adorned with their fruit, thou maiſt obſerve a ſtrong proofe to confirme thee in thy hope of a glorious reſurrection. If all other things doe ſhoote forth for man, then ſhall not man himſelfe revive and ſpring up? God who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored a vegetative life to <hi>Aarons</hi> rod when it was a drie ſticke,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Numb.</hi> 17.</note> cauſing it to bring forth buds, to bloome bloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomes, and to yeeld Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds, will much more raiſe <hi>Aaron</hi> himſelfe from the dead.
<note place="margin">Tamen abdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta quaedam vitalis ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat vis in ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicibus imis, et trunco ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſo nova vere tepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lulat arbos. <hi>Vida.</hi>
               </note> We are joyned unto Chriſt, who is the root: in the winter of death our life is hid in him; but when the time of refreſhing is come, we ſhall be raiſed to an eſtate of glory. <hi>Awake
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:176251:73"/>and ſing ye that dwell in duſt:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 26.19.</note> 
               <hi>for thy dew is as the dew of herbs, and the earth ſhall caſt out the dead.</hi> If we did looke unto the joy that is ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us, and by the eye of faith did ſee that recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of reward that is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved for us at that day, we would be more induſtrious in labouring to be filled with the fruits of righteouſneſſe, which are by Jeſus Chriſt, unto the praiſe and glory of God.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 11.1.</note> As they that caſt their bread upon the waters ſhall find it after many dayes, ſo they that have brought much fruit unto God in this life, ſhall have it reſtored un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them at the reſurrection of the juſt. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of having ſome fruit among the Romanes,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.13.</note> not onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:176251:73"/>he was an inſtrument to gather it, but alſo in regard of that gaine and advantage it would bring unto himſelfe at the latter end. Nothing can deprive us of this beſt fruit. The worme may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory our bodies, and the fruit of them, and may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the fruit of the ground: The worme of conſcience wil torment ſuch as brought forth fruit unto death by un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitfull workes of darknes; but this fruit is committed unto God, who is faithfull, and able to keepe it againſt that day.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.19.</note> Hereby we lay up in ſtore for our ſelves a good foundation againſt the time to come, that we may lay hold on eternall life.</p>
            <p>The world may be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to an Orchard, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:176251:74"/>the voluptuous man eats of the fruit with as much haſte and greedineſſe as was uſed by the Phariſees in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring Widowes houſes, or by the Iſraelites in eating their quails, as if they ſhould never take their fill of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights and pleaſures. The covetous wretch gathers with as much diligence as may be, filling his garments, and lading himſelf; but God hath not given him power to eat thereof: and when he comes to depart out at the door, he is not ſuffered to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry any part of that with him for which he laboured; On<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the godly man doth eat with moderation, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that as he came in, ſo he ſhall depart, and carry no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing out. He diſtributes to
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:176251:74"/>them that cannot help them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 30.12.</note> (as <hi>David</hi> gave the figs to the languiſhing E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptian) which afterward he finds againe for his future benefit: He doth exerciſe himſelfe in duties of charity, and extends his goodneſſe to the Saints that are in the earth, and the Lord doth render unto him glory, and honour, and peace. He that hath pitie on the poore, len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth unto the Lord,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 19.17.</note> and that which he hath given will he pay him again. If God doth account that to be done unto himſelfe which is done unto them, let us bring forth fruit unto God, which like the almes of <hi>Cornelius</hi> may come up for a memoriall before him. The fowles of the aire be as ready to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voure
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:176251:75"/>our fruit upon the trees, as our ſeed upon the ground. The Phariſees ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be full of good fruit, but then came the wicked one and tooke it away; they gave to the poore, but it was to this end, that they might have glory of men: they had their reward in being applauded here in this world. It was not likely that their fruit growing in ſo publike a place, ſhould come to the due perfection. Beware of vaine-glory and ſiniſter re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects: if thou doſt perceive any of theſe fowles to be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering about thy fruit, drive them away,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.</note> as <hi>Abraham</hi> did from the carkaſſes. Subdue all evill thoughts and vaine imaginations that may ariſe in thine heart: conſider, it is
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:176251:75"/>God which gives both the will and the deed; and all this ſtore that thou haſt, or giveſt, commeth of his hand, and is all his owne.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Chro</hi> 29.16.</note> Such as entertaine any arrogant con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits, are not onely robbed of the fruit and comfort of the preſent duty, but by nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing their impure corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, they doe endanger the tree it ſelf, and may deſtroy their owne ſoules: For ſin doth eat as doth a canker, ſpreading from the crowne of the head to the ſole of the foot, and entring even to the joints and marrow. This is to be cut out of the body, and to be cut off in the ſmaller branches. If thine eye offend thee, plucke it out; if thy right hand of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend thee, cut it off: in what
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:176251:76"/>part ſoever wee can diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any wickedneſſe, wee muſt take it away by the ſword of the Spirit, which is the Word of God. All fleſhly luſts are to bee van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed, our carnall mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers that are upon the earth muſt be mortified, and then whatſoever wee doe ſhall proſper: For if wee have been planted into the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Chriſts death,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.5.</note> wee ſhall be alſo in the likeneſſe of his reſurrection: If wee alwaies beare about in the body the dying of the Lord Jeſus,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.10.</note> then the life alſo of Jeſus ſhall be made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt in our body.</p>
            <p>Thus wee have conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red how Chriſt is the root, and wee are the branches graffed into him, deriving
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:176251:76"/>our being in this life, and our well-being in the life of grace, from his goodneſſe and mercy: Let us in the next place obſerve, how we our ſelves are the root, and the Word of God the cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which is put into us, that wee may be fruitfull. This we are warranted to doe by the teſtimony of St. <hi>James,</hi> who teacheth us to receive the engraffed word,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.21.</note> which is able to ſave our ſoules.</p>
            <p>Wee may well be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to the root; for as that is the moſt earthy part of the tree, ſo we by nature are of the earth, earthy, and have no good thing dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in this our fleſh;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.</note> but many ſinnes and corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that are deeply and ſtrongly rooted within us:
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:176251:77"/>and therefore may fitly bee reſembled unto ſome wild figge-tree, growing in the walls of a building, hiding and defacing the beauty thereof. The boughes and branches may bee cut and broken off; but the root, which is wrapped into the ſtones of the building, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee taken away, unleſſe the walls be thrown down: Even ſo ſinne is inwrapped into the joynts and entralls of this our building, into our nature, and the parts of it; and though we may lop off the branches, yet the root remaineth, while wee carry about this body of death: Sinne abideth untill our diſſolution. The ſcra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of the houſe within, would not take away the
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:176251:77"/>fretting leproſie;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Levit.</hi> 14.45</note> it muſt be broken downe: Our origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall concupiſcence cleaveth ſo cloſe to our nature, that it will never leave us, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till this earthly houſe bee demoliſhed. As the roots are diffuſed and ſpread a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad round about that place where the tree ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; ſo our corruptions are dilated into every part of the body, and faculty of the ſoule: And as the roots are covered in the earth; ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold ſins are hidden from the knowledge of men, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing workes of darkneſſe. The heart is deſperately wicked, who can know it?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.9.</note> The wiſdome of this world is earthly:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 3.17.</note>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.10.</note> The love of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney is the root of all evill; yea, every ſinne is a root of
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:176251:78"/>bitterneſſe, which if per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to ſpring up, will trouble us; As <hi>Jonah,</hi> when the weeds were wrapped about his head,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jonah</hi> 2.5.</note> prayed unto the Lord; ſo wee being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folded with our corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons muſt ſeeke unto God for deliverance. He is able to deſtroy the fruit from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, and the roots from beneath,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amos</hi> 2.9. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.24.</note> and to turne them into rottenneſſe and duſt, that they ſhall not have do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion over us. Such as the root is, ſuch are the bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches alſo: In the eſtate of our birth, before wee bee changed by the work of the Spirit, we are no better than the Crab-tree producing ſowre fruit; Our beſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances are impure and uncleane in Gods ſight. The
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:176251:78"/>Crab-ſtock is full of thorns; ſo we by nature are ſubject unto the curſe. It muſt be a divine power that can free us from condemnation, by renewing us in our minds, that wee may bring forth fruit meet for repentance. In graffing, all the branches that before did flouriſh are taken off, and uſually the ſtocke is cut downe not far from the ground; ſo wee are to be caſt downe in ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement of our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſſe, and to humble our ſelves as a little childe, that we may be partakers of the divine nature. This is intended by the Apoſtle, when he ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>James</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>Receive with meekneſs the engraffed word.</hi> When the heart is made lowly, it will be more ready
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:176251:79"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:176251:79"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="146" facs="tcp:176251:80"/>to receive the Word, &amp; the Word will be more ready to incorporate into it: Wee muſt not only lay aſide our greateſt ſins, our boaſting that we could do miſchiefe, our delight in folly and wickedneſſe; but alſo all confidence in our owne ſeeming vertues, as of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance, liberality, mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and the like, leſt we be puffed up thereby: See this in Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> who ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.3.</note> wee are the circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion who have no confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in the fleſh; and though he were blameleſſe touching the righteouſneſſe that was in the law; yet thoſe things that were gain to him, he counted loſſe for Chriſt. Thus <hi>David</hi> ſaith, His ſoule was even as a
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:176251:80"/>weaned childe; and thus we ſhould bee weaned and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtranged from taking any contentment in our owne ſtrength and ability; and ſhould put on (as the Elect of God, holy and beloved) humbleneſs of mind, meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and lowlineſſe. In the next place, there is an inciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or wound made into the ſtocke, by which it may be made capable and fitting to receive the cyons. In like manner, we muſt rend our hearts, and open our ſelves, that Chriſt may enter into our ſoules; Our hearts muſt be broken and opened, like the heart of <hi>Lydia,</hi> that we may receive the Word of life. Was Chriſt wounded for our tranſgreſſions? and ſhall not wee be pricked to
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:176251:81"/>the heart with ſorrow for our former provocations? After this, we put the cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons into that breach and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion that is made in the ſtocke; ſo after ſorrow and humiliation, God puts joy into our hearts, and his law into our inward parts, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planting his graces in our ſoules, and rejoycing over us to doe us good.
<note place="margin">Surculi vis ea eſt, ut in tantillo cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puſculo, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponderet arboris viri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus totius: Non enim arboris pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, ſed ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culi fructus. <hi>Scal. in Theoph. Bacon Cent.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Although the Cyon be ſmall in the beginning, yet it groweth to be a great tree, over-ruling the ſtocke, and bringing forth fruit of its owne kind; ſo although the beginning of grace be weak and little, like a graine of muſtard-ſeed, yet there is a continuall increaſing and growing unto more perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, when we yeeld our
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:176251:81"/>ſelves unto God, as thoſe that are alive from the dead, and our members as inſtruments of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, not living any longer in ſinne, but living by the faith of the Sonne of God, who loved us, and gave himſelfe for us, that hee might reconcile us, who were ſometimes alienated, and enemies in our minds by wicked workes, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livering us from the power of darkneſſe, might tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlate us into the Kingdome of his deare Sonne.</p>
            <p>As after graffing, the ſtocke being nigher unto the root than the cyons, and ſtill abiding in its proper place where it formerly did proſper, is ready to ſend forth many young twigs,
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:176251:82"/>that will arreſt and antici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate that ſtrength and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, which ſhould aſcend for the nouriſhment of the cyons, and are therefore di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently taken away to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent that miſchiefe: So there is a combat betweene the fleſh and the ſpirit, the one luſting againſt the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; there is the body of death, and the old leaven of corruption remaining within us. Our ſins and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities are continually in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſing, and hindring us from apprehending the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and love of God with that ſtrength and fulneſſe which wee doe deſire; and therefore wee muſt cut off theſe ſprigs with pruning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hookes; not ſuffering ſinne to reigne in our mortall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:176251:82"/>and have dominion o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver us; but mortifying the deeds of the body through the Spirit, and caſting down imaginations, and every high thing that exalteth it ſelfe againſt the knowledge of God, and bringing into captivity every thought to the obedience of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The Kingdome of God is compared to leaven hid in three meaſures of meale,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 13.21.</note> untill the whole were lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vened: A little leaven leave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the whole lump; the grace begun ſhould grow ſtrong and powerfull with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in us; the leaven of holineſs ſhould work out the leaven of malice. If the tree doth not flouriſh, we will impute the cauſe unto the barrennes of the ground, or the want
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:176251:83"/>of a good root,
<note place="margin">Craſsitie ſuâ cortex ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtat, quo mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus à terrae humore au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geatur aci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus; non enim tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittitur. <hi>Scal. in Theop.</hi>
               </note> or the thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the bark that binds the ſtocke; but not unto the graft it ſelf, which did grow very happily before it was converted to this uſe. From whence is it that there is ſuch imperfection &amp; weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? ſuch backwardneſſe in the good way? and that our fruits relliſh ſo much of the ſtocke, ſo little of the graft? Comes it not hence, that our corruptions and luſts doe ſtill warre in our members? and we doe not labour to perfect holineſſe in the feare of God? O wretched men, in whom the Croſſe of Chriſt hath not yet worne out the bitter taſte of that firſt tree! The Cyon is taken from the tree of life: Every good gift
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:176251:83"/>commeth downe from the Father of lights, who gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth liberally, and upbrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not: Oh that we were enlarged in apprehending and applying what is ſo freely offered: If our hearts were opened wide in holy deſires, the Lord would fill them with ſpirituall bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings; but wee are ſtraitned in our owne bowels; and being in this great ſtrait, we are as unable to free our ſelves, as the Prophet was to deliver himſelfe out of the belly of the Whale. We cannot relieve our ſelves, and vaine is the helpe of man, who is ſubject to the ſame miſery. We may not truſt to the arme of fleſh, or aſcribe the praiſe to humane power, as <hi>Adrian</hi> did, who
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:176251:84"/>wrote over his Hoſpitall at Lovan;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Adr.</hi> 6. Trajectum me planta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit, Lova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium me ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gavit, Caeſar incremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum dedit. Ergo Deus nihil fecit.</note> Utrecht planted, Lovan watered, <hi>Caeſar</hi> gave the increaſe: Whereunto it was fitly ſubſcribed by an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, Therefore God had nothing to doe in this man. We know, that neither hee that planteth is any thing, neither he that watereth, but God who giveth the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>So Noah be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to be an husbandman, and planted a vineyard. Gen.</hi> 9.20.</note> He is the Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, ſaith our Saviour; and we are his husbandry, ſaith the Apoſtle; both which places are to be underſtood of a Plantation, as appeares by the context, where it is ſaid,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 15.1.</note> That Chriſt is the Vine, and we the Branches, whereof hee purgeth ſome, and taketh away others. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo there is frequent menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of planting &amp; watering,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 39.</note>
               <pb n="155" facs="tcp:176251:84"/>which is ſome part of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie labour: And then the Apoſtle concludes, We are Gods husbandry, wee are Gods building; and except the Lord build the houſe, they labour in vaine that build it: Except the Lord gives a bleſſing, our paines and induſtry will be fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe. In demanding, who built ſuch an houſe, or plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſuch an orchard, we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend not the inferiour work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, but the chief owners, at whoſe expence they were performed; ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, although men may be labourers and workers with God, and ſome builders,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.9, 10. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.1.</note> and ſome maſter-builders; yet God is the ſupreme A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, working in us both to will and to doe, of his good
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:176251:85"/>pleaſure. Hee that built all things is God, who doth ſtill uphold them by the word of his power; who likewiſe planted Paradiſe, and the whole world, who ſends us yeerly the ſpring, and makes our gardens green, and our trees to flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.17.</note> He hath planted us in the mountaine of his inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, in the place which he hath made for himſelfe to dwell in.
<note place="margin">Terram preſsit, minus mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetur, &amp; ob hoe naſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes radices exire pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ac ſolum apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere. <hi>Senec. epiſt.</hi> 86.</note> And as trees in the beginning are ſurely fixed, that they may not be carried about of every wind, by meanes whereof the roots cannot be faſtened in the earth; ſo wee ought to ſtand faſt in the faith: which grace muſt bee wrought in us by the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.25.</note> who is of
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:176251:85"/>power to ſtabliſh,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.10. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.21.</note> ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, ſettle us, and to make us perfect in every good worke to doe his will. He is able to ſupply all our wants, and to work in us that which is well pleaſing in his ſight. Wherefore in the firſt place wee ſhould ſeeke unto the Lord for his ſupportati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that we may ſtand com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plete before him, and be tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly furniſhed unto every good work;
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim</hi> 2.6.</note> and then as the husbandman that laboureth muſt be firſt partaker of the fruits, ſo we, being enriched and ſtrengthened by the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine bleſſing and power, working in us mightily, muſt offer up our firſt-fruits in a ſacrifice of praiſe and thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving unto the Lord. Now as in the parables the Lord
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:176251:86"/>of the Vineyard hath his husbandmen and vine-dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers under him. So God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires that we ſhould be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent and induſtrious in la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring to bring forth good fruit.
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 27.28. Item vinito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus Schim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hi. i. exercen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus opus vinearum. <hi>Jun.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>David</hi> the King ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed <hi>Baal-hanan</hi> over the Olive trees and Sycomore trees, and <hi>Shimei</hi> over the Vineyards, who ruled and directed the inferiour labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, which did the worke that belonged thereunto. The Lord hath ordained his Miniſters to inſtruct us in the truth, and to declare all his counſell, not keeping backe any thing that is profitable unto us; and he expects our paines and endevours, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming what is evill, and in ſeeking for helpfull meanes for our furtherance in all
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:176251:86"/>godlineſſe and honeſty.
<note place="margin">Redit agri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colis labor actus in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bem. <hi>Virg.</hi>
               </note> There muſt be a continuall care and attendance in plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of an Orchard; the young trees muſt be aſsiſted and defended againſt the power of the wind, and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered in time of drought:
<note place="margin">Falce reſcin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendum, ne pars ſincera trahatur.</note> ſuch branches as wither ſhould be cut off: if any of the trees be dead, they muſt be renewed and ſupplied;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 13.8.</note> if barren, they muſt be helped, as the fig-tree was: Alſo by pruning, and other coſt, we ſhould repaire ſuch as begin to decline and ceaſe from yeelding fruit. Even thus is our condition:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.23.</note> Man goeth forth unto his work, &amp; to his labour untill the evening; I ſpeake not of bodily labour, and the ſweat of the face, without which we ſhould
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:176251:87"/>not eat our bread; but of the inward labour of the mind, which is more difficult, when we worke out our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation with feare and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling. And although we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin at the third houre, or ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the morning, yet we perſevere untill the evening, that we may be workmen which need not be aſhamed, being approved of God when he commeth and finds us ſo doing. If we did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the quantity of worke to be done, the manifold du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to be performed, the brevity of the time, and our owne weakeneſſe and unſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiencie, we would not be ſloathfull in this buſineſſe, nor expect any eaſe or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance untill the appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted time, in which we ſhall
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:176251:87"/>reſt from our labours. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we ought to be followers of that choſen veſſell who never deſiſted from his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and therefore might well joyne his watchings to his labours and painfulneſſe: For he was vigilant in his labours,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.5. &amp; 11.27.</note> and laborious in his watchings. When he had an auditory he ceaſed not to warne them night and day,
<note place="margin">Act. 20.11, 31. &amp; 16.25.</note> continuing his ſpeech untill midnight, yea, till the break of day; and when abſent from them,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.3.</note> at midnight he praiſed God, and night and day prayed for himſelfe and others. In ſo doing he was a follower of Chriſt, who that hee might finiſh the worke for which hee was ſent, he daily taught the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; and when others ſlept,
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:176251:88"/>he continued whole nights in prayer. If ſome men did thinke upon this, it might reſtraine them from conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming many nights in works of darkneſſe, that ſhall not be ſo much as named by me; and from ſpending ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny precious hours, and from ſpending many good dayes, and from ſpending many happy yeers, and from ſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a long life without the leaſt profit unto their ſoules. When there are ſo many expences, and nothing comming in all the time, no inward grace or bleſſing, what account will be given in the concluſion? The wicked Steward was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended for his wiſedome and providence, but theſe ungodly ſervants will be
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:176251:88"/>condemned for their folly. Let us lay this to heart, and ſhew forth our moderation in our lawfull and ſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble uſe, not in our inordinate and exceſſive abuſe of worldly pleaſures.
<note place="margin">Inſectatio hoſtium vel ferarum. <hi>Jun.</hi>
               </note> Although purſuing might hinder <hi>Baal</hi> from regarding of his ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, let it never take away our due regard of Gods ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice. To keepe us from love of vanity, and ſeeking after leaſing, we ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that work where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto we are called, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecting upon our ſelves, ſhould ſearch every part of the inward and outward man, ſeeking for redreſſe and amendment in that wherein we have revolted, and are defective. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we will begin with that
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:176251:89"/>part which is deepe and hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and requires moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act enquirie, as being the chiefe fountaine of all. For though the decay of a plant appeares firſt in the withe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the twigs and bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, yet it ariſeth, for the moſt part, from a decay in the root: ſo the decay of grace may appeare to the view firſt in our ſpeeches and carriage, yet the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall cauſe of the ſame is want of Gods feare, and weakeneſſe of faith in the heart. As the Mariners went downe into the ſides of the ſhip, where they found <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah</hi> faſt aſleep, who was the cauſe of all their trouble: ſo let us enter into the bottome of our heart by ſtrict exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, let us ſearch every
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:176251:89"/>corner thereof, as with a candle, that we may diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver our deadneſſe and ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, from whence this bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renneſſe in our converſation and uncomfortable walking before the Lord doe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed: when wee find any coldneſſe or backwardneſſe in Gods ſervice, we muſt be more inquiſitive in diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering that which hath ſtol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len away our graces, than <hi>Laban</hi> was in ſeeking for his gods.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 31.35.</note> No faire allegation may ſatisfie us, no goodly pretence may content us: There may be an image laid in the bed in the place of <hi>David:</hi> There may be a ſtrong deluſion in the heart, in ſtead of the lovely truth, or the lively grace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Saul</hi> was very diligent in
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:176251:90"/>ſeeking to find out him that did eate any food contrary to his unadviſed adjuration;
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.</note> but he did never looke into his owne heart to prove himſelfe, that he might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member from whence hee was fallen, and repent, and doe his firſt workes, ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thening the things that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained, which were ready to dye in him. Hee profeſt that he knew God, when in workes he denied him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing abominable and diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, and unto every good worke reprobate. He boaſts of performing the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, when he was curſed for doing the worke of the Lord negligently: God commands him to deſtroy <hi>Amaleck,</hi> but hee will ſave a King, though he
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:176251:90"/>loſe a Kingdome; Hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyeth that which was vile and refuſe, and ſpared the beſt of the ſheep and oxen for a ſacrifice unto the Lord, or rather unto Mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, out of avarice and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion. And, as if himſelfe were not ſo devout, hee ſaith, the people ſpared the beſt to ſacrifice, when as he is named to bee the chiefe agent in that confederacie. It may ſeem hee had little reaſon to ſpeake of a ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and to charge God thus fooliſhly and falſly,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.9, 15.</note> conſidering the little accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and bad ſucceſſe hee found after his forme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring. <hi>Samuel</hi> had told him, hee would come downe to Gilgal, and ſacrifice ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: yet hee would not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:176251:91"/>untill he came, but (without any warrant from Gods Word) hee forced himſelfe,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13.12</note> and offered burnt offerings: Whereupon the Prophet charged him with the breach of Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, and told him, his Kingdome ſhould not continue. Let his example admoniſh us to be vigilant in taking heed, leſt we leave our firſt love, and be begui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led of our reward: We can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be too carefull in trying our ſelves, and diſcovering any loſſe or impediment, whereby our ſpirituall eſtate is impaired. In the Parable there is a woman propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded worthy of our imitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who when ſhee had loſt one of her ten peeces of ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, ſhee ſought diligently
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:176251:91"/>till ſhee found it.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.72.</note> The Law of God is better than thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of gold and ſilver: If we have broken any one of the ten Commandements, wee ſhould ſeeke for Gods mercy in forgiving our tranſgreſſion, and reſtoring unto us the joy of his ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and ſhould rejoyce more in his love, delivering us from perdition and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, than any one doth that findeth great ſpoiles. The Image of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning was ſtamped upon man, and the ſuperſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his power and domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, by which hee did ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend that loyaltie and ſubjection, which was due to the King of glory. Now ſince our gold became
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:176251:92"/>droſſe, that inſcription was obliterate, and that image defaced, which is againe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed by the merits of Chriſt, who gave himſelfe for us, that hee might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem us from all iniquity, and purifie unto himſelfe a peculiar people, zealous of good workes. As hee hath purged our ſinnes,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3.</note> ſo he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects that wee alſo ſhould purifie our hearts,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.8.</note> and purge our ſelves from all evill, that wee may bee prepared unto every good worke.
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.21.</note> There are divers and ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry helpfull meanes to bee uſed about the roots of trees,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plin. Sec. l.</hi> 17. <hi>c.</hi> 27. <hi>de ſtercoratione.</hi>
               </note> and ſome eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly belonging to particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar trees, either to revive them, and make them flouriſh, or to cauſe them
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:176251:92"/>to beare fruit, or to melio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and amend their fruit: In ſuch great choice, I will ſelect thoſe two, which are mentioned by the Dreſſer of the vineyard, who ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 13.8.</note> 
               <hi>I will digge about the figge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree, and dung it:</hi> Not that he intends to digge about it, only to make way for that which he ſhould apply unto the root;
<note place="margin">In laxiore ſolo plantae laetiores, in denio ſaepe ſtrangulan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Fitque quaſi nova terra quae vetus erat; Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polatur, enim Aer edomat, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mul imbres patitur.</note> but when either of theſe remedies apart, and both together are commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious, hee would uſe them joyntly for the more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine cure of that barren tree: Firſt then we obſerve, that digging about the roots is very beneficiall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the tree, which is apt to bee ſtrangled in a ſtiffe and ſtubborne earth, where the root can find no paſſage to
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:176251:93"/>ſpread it ſelfe;
<note place="margin">Denſato ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo in cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtam, nequit ſubire ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum. <hi>Scal. in Theop.</hi>
               </note> but growes very kindly in a looſe earth, that is refreſhed and diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by this meanes, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes more capable of the ſhowers, and made every way more favourable unto the plant.
<note place="margin">Etiam radi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidiſſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt. <hi>Plin. Sec.</hi>
               </note> Alſo ſuch of the leſſer roots as are cut aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, doe ſend forth many ſmall ſtrings, which diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſe themſelves in the ground, and are effectuall for the good of the tree. Now if men bee thus indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious in labouring to make their trees fruitfull, then we ought to uſe all meanes poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible (ſo much as in us lieth) that our hearts may bee fruitfull; Let us put off the old man with his deeds, and put on the new man, which is renewed in knowledge;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 3.10.</note>
               <pb n="173" facs="tcp:176251:93"/>and be carefull to maintaine good workes,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.8.</note> that are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable unto us. This dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging about the tree may fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bee repreſented by that which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> writes in his two Epiſtles to <hi>Timothy:</hi> In the former he ſaith,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14.</note> 
               <hi>Neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect not the gift that is in thee;</hi> Let not the grace of God in thine heart be there buried, as dead earth, that lies at the root of the tree, and is not profitable: And not ſatisfied with that which hee had ſpoken be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, in the ſecond Epiſtle he doth againe preſſe upon him that former exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, with a deſcription of the manner how it ought to be performed,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.6.</note> 
               <hi>I put thee in remembrance, that thou ſtirre up the gift of God which is in
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:176251:94"/>thee;</hi> as the earth is ſtirred in digging: If there be any power or vertue therein, it will then appeare. If there bee any grace or holineſſe, wee ſhould excite the ſame by the worke of the quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Spirit: Doe not thou abide in a dead eſtate void of the new life; but come forth with <hi>Lazarus,</hi> ariſe out of the grave of corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that God may be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified by thy good conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation. In the next place he ſaith, Hee will dung the figge-tree, that it may beare fruit. I intend not to rehearſe the ſeverall ſubſtances, which are nominated by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers
<note n="*" place="margin">Lotium ſuillum aut ſtercus ad arborum ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices addi praecipit, ut Favulum malorum fiat, &amp;c. <hi>Cato.</hi> Vel Pabulum malorum, <hi>i.e.</hi> pro cibo (vel quod immundo lotio mala delectentur.) <hi>Turneb.</hi> Stercoratio fit ex animanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um excrementis, vel è ſtipulis, culmis, aut terrae medullá.</note> Authors, as condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing to fructification, when
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:176251:94"/>laid about the roots of the trees; being ſo applyed, there is vertue and efficacie in them: but here to ſet them downe, would not yeeld that profit which I moſt deſire: As they are to be covered in the earth; ſo they ſhall bee concealed from the Readers view, and paſſed over in ſilence; My principall aime is to doe good in amending the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren heart, rather than the barren earth: Wherefore let us attempt to draw ſome benefit unto our ſelves. The Apoſtle tells us what he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts to bee dung,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.8.</note> Even all his own worthineſſe and workes, all his owne privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges and prerogatives whatſoever: He was ſo far from being exalted above
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:176251:95"/>meaſure by them, that hee rather caſts them downe to the root, and eſteems them of no value: And ſurely, he was a plant of renowne, rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed up by the Lord, whoſe height reached unto hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, when hee was caught up into Paradiſe it ſelfe; whoſe leaves were faire, and his fruit much, prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the Goſpel to many Nations; yet hee aſſumes not any praiſe to himſelfe, but gives the glory to God: Hee doth not attribute his good fruit to any humane power, but to the divine mercy; Not to any inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our cauſe in himſelfe, but to the Sunne of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which ſhined upon him, who before was in darkneſſe. The humble
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:176251:95"/>heart is moſt fruitfull; when wee are abaſed in ſenſe of our owne inſufficiency, we ſhall be enriched with Gods favour: Such as truſt wholly to their proper gifts, doe reſt upon the foot of pride, which will ſlip a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and overthrow them; Much of that hot ſubſtance applyed doth conſume the root, and deſtroy the tree: They that are high-minded, and conceited of their abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, doe ſeeke their owne ſubverſion: Wee ſhould be ſo farre from aſcribing any excellency or dignity to our owne power,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 8.17.</note> and the might of our hand, that we ſhould rather in all lowli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe confeſſe, that wee are all as an uncleane thing,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 64.6.</note> and all our righteouſneſſes are as
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:176251:96"/>filthy rags. There is juſt cauſe to be humbled and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſed when wee obſerve how barren we have made the earth by our ſins, ſo that we are conſtrained to uſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers compounds and ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients (the naming wherof would be offenſive) of very meane eſtimation, to help to revive it, and reſtore it to ſome part of its former ſtrength and vigour.</p>
            <p>In like maner we may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waile and lament the dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and perverſeneſſe of our hearts, whenas all the furtherance and comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble encouragement we can uſe is not ſufficient to recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie them, and bring them to good perfection. So great is their crookedneſſe they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be made ſtraight; ſo
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:176251:96"/>many are the graces wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, they cannot be num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred. And yet we muſt not couch downe under our bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, for then our field will be all growne over with thornes, and the face there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of will be covered with net<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, and the ſtone wall will be broken down; our ſoules will be filled with vice and impietie: But let us with much labour ſeeke to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme what is out of order, and to ſupply what is defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive;
<note place="margin">Laudato in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentia rura, Exiguum co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lito. <hi>Virg.</hi> Quae cura totum poſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat virum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi. <hi>Baudius.</hi>
               </note> that as the heart is one of the little members of the body, ſo it may be like the poore mans ſmall tenement, well manured.</p>
            <p>It is a common practice to lay ſome choice earth and good mould about the roots of the trees, that they may
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:176251:97"/>grow,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4.</note> and be fruitfull: ſo we ſhould apply unto our ſelves the exceeding great and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious promiſes which God hath given unto us,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.7.</note> and the exceeding riches of his grace which he hath ſhewed in his kindneſſe towards us, through Chriſt Jeſus; and thereby we ſhall find vertue to come into our ſoules, and ſhall be enabled to bring forth good fruit.</p>
            <p>Leaving the root, we will contemplate the body of the tree, and from thence we will aſcend unto the branches.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bacon cent. v.</hi> 440. Vectigal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercipit ſibi vafer ille a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trienſis, heri ſobole de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſo ſuo defraudato. <hi>Scal. in The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>op.</hi>
               </note> It is an uſuall pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice to hacke the trees in the barke, both downeright and acroſſe, which doth great good to trees, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially delivereth them from being bark-bound, and
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:176251:97"/>killeth their moſſe. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing wee may performe which ſhall in part be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable hereunto. I intend not to approve of their cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome who ſcourge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 18.28.</note> as the Prieſts of <hi>Baal</hi> did cut themſelves with knives and lancers, till the bloud guſhed out upon them; which is like that humour of <hi>Artaxerxes,</hi> who would have the robes of his Nobles ſcourged for ſuch offences as their bodies ſhould be beaten;
<note place="margin">In corde, non in cortice.</note> Our wounds muſt pierce deeper than the barke, even to the heart, which muſt be rent by contrition. There may be an inward bruiſe, though there bee no outward breach: there may be true compunction without vaine
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:176251:98"/>oſtentation. The Phariſees did diſ-figure their faces when they faſted,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.16.</note> by art they compoſed themſelves to looke pale and leane, that they might appeare unto men to faſt;
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.27.</note> But Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> not regarding mans day, did keepe under his body, and bring it into ſubjection: So we by faſting &amp; humiliation ſhould ſubdue the body, that the ſoules burthen may be light, and the yoke eaſie, when the body doth not rule as a tyrant, but is ready to goe and come like a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, we cut off ſuch branches as are not profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and the water-boughs, which are overſhadowed by the ſuperiour branches: ſo we muſt lay aſide all earthly
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:176251:98"/>affections, and carnall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires; And as the reapers in Gods harveſt doe gather out all things that offend,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.41.</note> ſo wee his husbandmen ought to cut off all corrupt and unfruitfull branches, all wicked actions and worldly cares, whereby we may be overcharged and hindred from obtaining true happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.2.</note> God hath given the pruning hooke into the hand of the Church, that it may have power to take away wicked perſons from among us: And God hath put the pruning hook into the hand of every Chriſtian, to judge, and trie, and prove himſelfe, that he might reject and caſt off all impiety, deſtroying the fleſh, that the ſpirit may bee ſaved in the day
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:176251:99"/>of the Lord Jeſus.</p>
            <p>As it is required that we ſhould thus labour to make our ſelves fruitfull; ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe we muſt be induſtrious in ſeeking to bring them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſame good condition which are committed to our charge;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 22 6.</note> eſpecially to traine up our children in the way they ſhould goe, and when they are old they will not depart from it:
<note place="margin">Quae laceris ramis, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrictoque ardua libro Certatim fundis per latus omne petor. Infelix, fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus in mea damna fero. <hi>Alciat.</hi>
               </note> If we neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect the performance here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, we may feare that will come upon us which doth befall divers trees, whoſe branches are broken, and they ſmitten and beaten, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the fruit that grew upon them: ſo we ſhould be puniſhed for the tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our children,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.31.</note> as <hi>Eli</hi> was, who neglected to prune
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:176251:99"/>and correct his ſonnes, and therefore the Lord did threaten to cut off his arme, and the arme of his fathers houſe; hee did not chaſtiſe them for their apoſtaſie and back-ſliding from the right way, and therefore he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, by Gods judgement upon him, fell backward, and his neck brake, and hee died. The chiefe care of the parent muſt be to bring up that young nurcerie in the nurture and admonition of the Lord:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.4.</note>
               <note place="margin">Perſicus &amp; prunus ex oſsibus opti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae. <hi>Scal. in Theop.</hi>
               </note> that as the peach and ſome plumbs are good ariſing from the ker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell; ſo they from their childhood may know the holy Scripture, which is able in that tender age to make them wiſer than their tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, and to underſtand
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:176251:100"/>more than the ancients. Trees not regarded become crooked and unfruitfull; but duely tended, they grow to perfection. The branch at firſt ſhooting out is tender and flexible, but at laſt it growes to a hard and ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne bough.
<note place="margin">Ut corpora ad quoſdam membrorum flexus forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, niſi tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra, non poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunt. <hi>Quintil.</hi>
               </note> In the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding if any member of their body grow out of order, we will be carefull to ſeeke for help, before their joynts be knit, and their bones bee ſtiffe; Oh let us be as provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent for their ſoules as we are prudent for their bodies. What is <hi>Abſaloms</hi> beauty, or <hi>Sauls</hi> ſtature, without <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> wiſedome? <hi>David</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 128.3.</note> thy children ſhalbe like Olive plants round about thy table: not like the tall Cedar, but the fruitfull
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:176251:100"/>Olive; Their praiſe and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity ſhall not conſiſt in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward forme and comeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but in heavenly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments and divine gifts; and being ſo qualified, they may well be likened to the Olive, the fatneſſe whereof was uſed to honour God in ſacrifices, and to make the face ſhine in annointing.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Judg.</hi> 9.9.</note> They doe ſeeke to advance Gods glory,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.15.</note> and they make their father rejoice, and have a cheerefull countenance, when they behold them walking in all the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements and ordinances of God blameleſſe.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 144.12.</note> If we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire our ſons may bee as plants growne up in their youth, we muſt command them to keepe the way of the Lord; and as wee are
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:176251:101"/>burning lights by godly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, ſo we muſt be ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning lights by vertuous ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample. For what they have ſeene us doe, they will make haſt to doe as we have done. Be not too indulgent; you ſee how <hi>Adonijah</hi> rewarded his fathers love,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 1.6.</note> who had not diſpleaſed him in ſaying, Why haſt thou done ſo? And yet he would diſpleaſe his father, and though not in word yet in deed would queſtion his authority in diſpoſing of the kingdome to <hi>Solomon,</hi> who was choſen by the Lord God of Iſrael. We have had fathers of our fleſh which corrected us,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.9.</note> and we gave them reverence; It may be the more reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence for their correction, when it was without provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:176251:101"/>or diſcouragement. There is no young tree that doth not ſend forth ſome twigs that would be cut off; In youth there is ſomething to be taken away. Doe not adde the evill of rioting and exceſſe unto the vanity of youth. Such as bring them up in luxury,
<note place="margin">Vinoirrigare conſuevit. <hi>Macrob.</hi> Tantumque honoris in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crevit, ut me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro infuſo enutriantur. <hi>Plin. Sec. Eſay</hi> 16.9.</note> deale by their children as <hi>Hortenſius</hi> did by his trees, who powred wine to the roots of them in ſtead of water. We ſhould rather imitate the Prophet, who ſaith, <hi>I will water thee with my teares, O Heſhbon.</hi> We muſt bewaile their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, and be humbled for our former ſins; Conſider from what ſtocke they did proceed, and when we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold their infirmities, let us remember that ſuch were
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:176251:102"/>ſome (if not all) of us; But we are waſhed,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11.</note> but we are ſanctified, but we are juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the name of the Lord Jeſus, and by the ſpirit of our God. Our planting and watering, and all our labour about them will be vaine, unleſſe God give the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe.
<note place="margin">Multae iſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum arboaum meâ manu ſunt ſatae. <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cero. Plutar. in Artax.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Cyrus</hi> might ſpeake of the trees planted by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, but his owne name (in the Perſian tongue) did put him in mind of the Sunne, without whoſe influence the work of his hands could not proſper. God is able to change <hi>Benoni</hi> into <hi>Benja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min,</hi> to make thy ſonne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a plant of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; The child of ſo many prayers, of ſo many teares, cannot miſcarry: Thou maiſt thinke thy ſons heart to be as
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:176251:102"/>dead and barren as <hi>Sarahs</hi> wombe: The Lord, who ſtrenthened her to bring forth <hi>Iſaac,</hi> is able by the operation of the Spirit to forme Chriſt in his heart, cauſing you both to laugh and rejoyce.</p>
            <p>There is ſome fruit that is harſh and unſavoury when it is gathered, but uſefull and pleaſant after it hath been kept a long time: Although for the preſent thy ſon bee as grievous un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, as <hi>Eſau</hi> to his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; yet through the Lords mercy hee may hereafter prove as comfortable and obedient, as <hi>Joſeph</hi> to his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. In the laſt place, I will adde another care and charge of the Parent, which is the firſt and laſt, yea the
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:176251:103"/>onely aime and deſire of moſt men, who labour to perform, or rather to pervert that place, where it is ſaid, <hi>Fathers ought to lay up for their children;</hi> that as the branches derive their ſap and nouriſhment from the root, ſo children ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive ſome eſtate &amp; means from their parents: Which ought to be done decently and in order; Not that the father,
<note place="margin">Quae quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum vertice ad auras Aethereas, tantum ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice in tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tara tendit. <hi>Virg.</hi>
               </note> like an earth-worm, ſhould be hidden as the root under ground, living in wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full penury and obſcurity, that afterward his branches may flouriſh in greatneſſe, and ſpread themſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad. He is worſe than an Infidell, that provides not for his family; and hee is worſe than an Infidell, that
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:176251:103"/>doth provide for his family in this manner, when hee forgets to diſtribute to the neceſſity of the Saints, and excludes all works of piety and charity: thinking that there is but one thing need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, which is, to bee trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled about many things, to be overcharged with cares, to bee entangled with worldly affaires, to eate the bread of ſorrowes, that he may heap up riches, and the glory of his houſe may be increaſed: He ſeekes not for the beginning and increaſe of grace, but placeth his godlineſſe in gaine, and u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth all crooked waies and ſiniſter meanes to obtaine his wretched ends, <hi>viz.</hi> that his eſtate, which formerly was ſmall as a grain of mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtard-ſeed,
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:176251:104"/>may wax a great tree,
<note place="margin">Ramorum pondera adeo in ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram curvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ut annuo ſpatio infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantur, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vamque ſibi propaginem faciant circa parentem. <hi>Scal. exer. de Indica ficu. Mangle in Purchas.</hi>
               </note> and ſhoot out great branches; and ſo in the end become like that tree, whoſe branches ſpreading from the body, doe bend themſelves downwards to the earth, where they take hold, and with new rooting multiply themſelves into a wood;
<note place="margin">Arbore de rais.</note> They enlarge their borders, joyning houſe to houſe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.8.</note> and field to field, till there be no place, that they may be placed alone in the midſt of the earth. The plant which was a long time in growing up, may ſoon be hewen downe:
<note place="margin">Et quas fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacis colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git lingua parentis, Has eadem nati lingua refudit opes. <hi>Claudian.</hi> Dirae filius eſt rapacita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis. <hi>Martial.</hi>
               </note> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more uſuall than for the ſonne to cut downe thoſe trees, which were cheriſhed and maintained by the father; to waſte that
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:176251:104"/>ſubſtance with riotous li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, which was gotten with avarice and rapine: wherefore bee not herein juſt overmuch, neither make thy ſelfe over-wiſe: Wholly to caſt our ſelves upon the Lord, and to neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect all lawfull meanes, is a preſumptuous temptation: Againe, to ſacrifice to our net, and truſt to our owne wiſedome, not leaving any ſpace where God may worke by his power and providence, is a deſperate contempt of the divine bleſſing, which is the beſt inheritance.
<note place="margin">Fortunam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> avidè vora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re pergas, eandem ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lè conco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quas neceſſe eſt. <hi>Sincer. Job</hi> 20.15, 28.</note> Hee that hath ſwallowed downe riches, ſhall vomit them up again: God ſhall caſt them out of his belly. The increaſe of his houſe ſhall depart, and
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:176251:105"/>his goods ſhall flow away in the day of his wrath. If God prepares a worme to ſmite the tree, it withereth: If hee blowes upon the ſame, it periſheth ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and comes utterly to an end.</p>
            <p>This is the concluſion of the covetous man, and the ſame confuſion belongs to all other ungodly men:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.35. Luco dile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctior omni Laurus hane imo ſtipite caeſam vidit. <hi>Claudian.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>I have ſeene the wicked in great power, and ſpreading himſelfe like a green bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree; yet he paſſed away, and loe he was not: yea, I ſought him, but hee could not bee found:</hi> Such men may bee compared unto that tree, which doth ever beare leaves, and never any fruit; ſo they may make ſhew of piety, and ſeem to be reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious,
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:176251:105"/>but doe not bring forth the fruit of the Spirit. The Bay-tree proſpers beſt in the ſhade; ſo they ſeeke not to be enlightened from above, and to have the Sun of Righteouſneſſe ariſe and ſhine into their hearts:
<note place="margin">Traditur non feriri ipſam à ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine. <hi>Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſtor.</hi>
               </note> That tree is not blaſted nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed by lightning; ſo they are not moved nor awake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, when they heare Gods judgements denounced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſinners: But as the ancient Conquerours were crowned with Laurell;
<note place="margin">Hâc victores Delphi co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronari, &amp; triumphan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes Romae. <hi>Plin. Sec.</hi>
               </note> ſo they doe triumph as victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious when with their car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall weapons they ſeem to overcome ſuch as they thinke to be their enemies, becauſe they tell them the truth, breaking their bands aſunder, and caſting their
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:176251:106"/>cords from them: yet let them remember, that as the branches of this tree are uſed in ſolemnities of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing and mourning; ſo their preſent ſolace and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light may ſoon be finiſhed, and they bee called to ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and lamentation. The Bay-trees, which for many yeeres have flouriſhed, are ſmitten by a great froſt, and doe wither away;
<note place="margin">En frigidus orbes, Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pureos jam ſomnus obit. <hi>Val. Flac.</hi> Corpus ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne animae frigus letale ſecutam eſt. <hi>Ovid.</hi>
               </note> Such as heretofore have lived in proſperity, and enjoyed their health and ſtrength, may ſoon bee ſurprized by that cold ſleep, and have their bodies benummed by death; After which, as the Bayes doth crackle &amp; make a noiſe when it is burnt;
<note place="margin">Laurus Terribili ſonitu flam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mâ crepi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tante cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matur. <hi>Lucret.</hi>
               </note> ſo they, being caſt into un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenchable fire, ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:176251:106"/>in weeping, and wail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and gnaſhing of teeth:
<note place="margin">Fragiles in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cende bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumine lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ros. <hi>Virg.</hi> Quod inter urendum fragorem edunt. <hi>Turne.</hi>
               </note> There ſhall bee deſperate yellings, and hideous out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cries; the mighty voice of Thunder, the raging of the Sea, the Cataracts of Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus, the ſound of the Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, the roaring of Lions, howling of Wolves, low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Oxen, barking of Dogges, all the moſt dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and offenſive clamours in the world are not to bee compared to the torments that ſhall be inflicted upon the ſonnes of perdition in this their ſenſe of Hearing. In the time of their life God gave them this ſenſe, by which faith doth enter into the ſoule: Eares they had, but not an eare to heare and hearken to the
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:176251:107"/>Word of truth; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore neglecting to improve this gift to their comfort and ſalvation, they are juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly therein puniſhed after their deceaſe: Not labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring now to receive good things thereby, afterward they receive evill things. When ſuch as ſtand in the way of ſinners, doe heare what evill of puniſhment the Lord doth threaten to bring upon the impenitent, I wiſh that both their eares may tingle, that they may be moved with horrour &amp; fear of the vengeance of eternall fire; &amp; having a ſpace given them to repent, if not for love of God, and the joy that is ſet before us, yet for dread of the fiery indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that they may returne
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:176251:107"/>unto the Lord in an accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted time, while they may be heard, before that day doth overtake them, in which they ſhall be as farre from ſuccour, as from audience.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi> 8.9.</note> Our daies upon earth are a ſhadow, whereof we may fitly be admoniſhed by this green tree, whoſe leaves do never fall: Wee may ſoone be changed from a flouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing to a languiſhing eſtate; and therefore as this tree doth produce ſome berries for medicine, though not for meat; ſo let us bring forth fruit meet for repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, that the diſeaſes of our ſoules may bee healed, and the iſſue of our corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions may be ſtopped.</p>
            <p>It may be expected, that as we have compared wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:176251:108"/>men in generall unto this Bay-tree mentioned by <hi>David;</hi> ſo we ſhould now deſcend to ſome particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, that wee may ſee ſuch men, as trees, walking; as the blind man of Bethſaida did,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mar.</hi> 8.24.</note> when hee began to be reſtored to his ſight. It is true, that ſuch men are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled to divers kinds of trees: As the proud man to the Cedars of Lebanon,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 2.13.</note> and the Oakes of Baſhan; The ambitious to the Bramble,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Judg</hi> 9.15.</note> and the like: But within the compaſſe of our ground we deſire to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine only ſuch trees as are fruitfull. Wee will herein follow the example of Chriſt, who oft-times re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorted to the garden with his Diſciples; not of <hi>John</hi>
               <pb n="203" facs="tcp:176251:108"/>the Baptiſt, who went into the wilderneſſe: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore omitting to ſpeake of wild and barren trees, we will apply our ſelves unto the Vine,
<note place="margin">Fructum vitis qui prae ali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus excellit. <hi>Calvin.</hi>
               </note> whoſe fruit being rightly uſed, doth excell the fruit of all other trees, and is ſaid to cheare both God and man; God in a drink offering, and man when hee doth uſe it with moderation: and is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore preſcribed to be given unto thoſe that be of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie hearts, that they may forget their miſery: But as commonly abuſed, it is the poyſon of Dragons, and the cruel venome of Aſpes; At the laſt it bites like a Serpent,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 23.32.</note> and ſtings like an Adder. The bloud of the grape doth occaſion ſuch as
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:176251:109"/>exceed therein,
<note place="margin">Res epulis quondam, nunc bello &amp; caedibus apta. <hi>Ovid.</hi>
               </note> to powre out their owne bloud, and to ſhed the bloud of other men. And as this plant is not able to ſubſiſt without ſome ſupportation; ſo the bodies of ſuch as doe tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe thereby, are made weake and unable to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold themſelves: Alſo their underſtanding is dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by clouds and vapours, aſcending from the dead ſea of a defiled body, which doe hinder the influence of the divine light upon their ſoules.</p>
            <p>In former times, they that were drunken, were drunken in the night;
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.7.</note> but now ſinne is growne impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and that evill which heretofore was ſecretly committed, is now acted
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:176251:109"/>before all Iſrael, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Sunne. It would be ſuperfluous to attempt any further diſcovery of this beſtiall pollution (I may be taxed of errour in calling it beſtiall,
<note place="margin">Omne bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum à vino naturaliter abhorret. <hi>Aelian.</hi>
               </note> becauſe every beaſt doth abhorre wine) when as the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors themſelves have nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will nor power to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale their ſinne from the view of all men. I will not ſubſcribe to the practice of <hi>Lycurgus,</hi> who to reduce his ſubjects to ſobriety, cauſed all the Vines to be rooted up:
<note place="margin">Edixit ne quis in Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liâ novella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret. <hi>Sue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on.</hi> Nervii, ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil patiuntur vini inferri. <hi>Sic Suevi. Caeſar de bel. Gal. l.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp; l.</hi> 4.</note> Nor to <hi>Domiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> Edict, that none might plant Vineyards: Nor yet to that cuſtome of divers Nations, who interdicted the importation of wine; but as the ſmell of the Vine
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:176251:110"/>in the time of its flouriſhing doth drive away Serpents and venemous Creatures; ſo it would be a great hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, if theſe impure wretches were prohibited from partaking of this good fruit, that maketh glad the heart of man: and then, as by Gods gracious providence, our Vines in this Land are not, Now, hurtfull unto the people by producing wine; ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the people may not be hurtfull unto the Land by their provocation of Gods anger to puniſh them for their uncleanneſſe; but we all may be free from intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance herein: and if any, that only ſuch Nations,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.3.</note> as have drunke of the wine of the wrath of the cup of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication,
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:176251:110"/>may exceed in the abuſe of the wine that growes among them. And yet I would to God that they alſo were the Lords people, and altogether like unto us (or ſuch as we then ſhould be) in being delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from the bonds of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall and corporall drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe. While I reprove this exceſſe in others, I my ſelfe may ſeem to exceed and to wander from my preſent purpoſe; but the Vine (whereof wee now treat) is a luxuriant plant,
<note place="margin">Serpentem multipliei lapſu &amp; er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratico. <hi>Cicero</hi>
               </note> whoſe branches runne far. A large digreſſion may be tolerable in me, when I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend a great tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that is into lerable in very many. Having related what harme and loſſe it
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:176251:111"/>brings to others, we will now enter upon our vintage, and ſee what gaine and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit may redound unto our ſelves.</p>
            <p>The Church in divers places of Scripture is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled unto a Vine that was planted by God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,
<note place="margin">Ferro ampu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans coercet ars agrico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larum, ne ſylveſcat farmentis. <hi>Cicero.</hi> Niſi putetur ſylveſcit, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ut lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damus, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruſceſcit. <hi>Scal in Theop.</hi>
               </note> who doth fence it and beſtow coſt upon it, &amp; looks that it ſhould bring forth grapes. There is no plant that requires ſuch frequent pruning as the Vine, which will become wild and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitfull if the looſe and ſpreading branches be not cut off every yeere. By which we are againe put in remembrance how needfull correction is for us, leſt this pleaſant plant, this noble vine, bee tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:176251:111"/>into the degenerate plant of a ſtrange Vine;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.21.</note> leſt we waxe wanton againſt the Lord, and forget him that nouriſhed us, and brought us up. Now no chaſtening for the preſent ſeemeth to be joyous,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.11.</note> but grievous; nevertheleſſe, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward it yeeldeth the peaceable fruit of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe unto them that are exerciſed thereby. The goodly cluſter may ſeeme to be ſpoiled, being caſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the wine-preſſe to bee cruſhed and ſtrained, when as by that meanes comes forth the new wine, which is ſo uſefull and comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; but if it had remained as before, it would have beene of ſhort duration and ſmall benefit. So then both
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:176251:112"/>from the tree and the fruit we may conclude that affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions are good for us, and are a teſtimony that we are ſons,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.6, 7.</note> and ſuch ſons as are beloved of our father; though ſome twigs be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken off, other more profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble will ſhoot forth in their place. God who is able to graffe thoſe branches in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine that before were bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken off, is likewiſe able to make other branches ſpring up in lieu of them that were taken away. It is better for the Vine to be pruned, and ſtill to grow in a fat and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile ſoile, than not being dreſt and tended,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 19.12, 13.</note> at laſt to be pluckt up in furie, and planted in the wilderneſſe in a dry and thirſty ground. It is better that the branch
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:176251:112"/>ſhould be purged by the husbandman, that it may bring forth more fruit,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 15.2.</note> than to ſuffer the Vine, being not regarded, to be rooted up by the Bore of the foreſt, and troden downe by the wild beaſt of the field. It is better to be chaſtened of the Lord, than condemned with the world. In time of perſecution, or the greateſt extremity, there is an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of comfort from the Vine: for as that in winter ſeemes to be more ſeere and drie than any other tree, as if it were fit for nothing but the fire; yet in the ſpring it recovers the former beauty, growing more, and putting out the branches further than any other tree that is fruitfull: Even ſo when we
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:176251:113"/>are preſſed out of meaſure, above ſtrength, in ſo much that we deſpaire of life; yet even then God who raiſeth the dead, is able to deliver us from ſo great a death; He that can make the withered branches to ſhoot out, and the drie bones to live, can alſo raiſe us, even when we are loweſt, unto an eſtate of conſolation and thankſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving.</p>
            <p>The Church is like a Vine, and every Congregation may be compared unto a cluſter, in which many grapes doe grow together. So the people ought to be firmly knit together in love and unity, to draw their nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment from the ſame root,
<note place="margin">Fulgentes ſole race<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos. <hi>Silius.</hi>
               </note> and to be ripened by the ſame influence of the
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:176251:113"/>Sun, and to be refreſhed by the ſame dew of the divine grace. Although the Spies which were ſent by <hi>Moſes,</hi> and brought the cluſter of grapes out of the land of promiſe, did not partake of the bleſſings of that land; yet Gods meſſengers, who doe carry theſe cluſters into the heavenly Canaan, ſhall for ever enjoy the felicity of that better Country.</p>
            <p>If we take the Church to be the Vineyard, (as it is oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times called) then we muſt conſider every true beleever to be a Vine, unto which he may well be likened.
<note place="margin">Ut ex eâ flu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at quod ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mium eſt. <hi>Scal. in Theop.</hi>
               </note> For as in graffing of the Vine it was uſuall to let the ſtocke, in regard of the aboundant moiſture, to bleed divers dayes before the Cyons was
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:176251:114"/>faſtened thereunto; ſo there is a time of mourning be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord doth put joy into the heart. We doe firſt lay apart all filthineſſe, and ſuperfluity of naughtineſſe, before we receive the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graffed word. This is the weakeſt of all plants, and muſt be ſuſtained by the ſides of the houſe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 128.3. Jamjam con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingit ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum radice flagellum. <hi>Catul.</hi> Qualiter ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaevo ſocia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam palmite vitem Ultuus amat. <hi>Stati.</hi>
               </note> (as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> ſpeaketh) or by ſome wall, or frame, or ſuch like ſtay, or elſe be joyned to ſome tree: ſo we being fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and infirme in our ſelves, are ſupported by the favour and goodneſſe of God. Such as make fleſh their arme, or truſt to any out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward help,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 7.17.</note> doe as <hi>Joram</hi> did, who leaned upon the hand of that man which was ſoone trodden downe:
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:176251:114"/>That ſhore and ſtrength upon which they reſted may ſuddenly be taken away from them.
<note place="margin">Si quid atti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerit ultrò amabit, &amp; quidem viri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſius am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexabitur, &amp;c. <hi>Tertul.</hi>
               </note> The Vine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus weake in it ſelfe, doth by the tendrels or ſmall ſtrings ſeeke to catch hold upon any thing it doth touch, and to graſp it faſt,
<note place="margin">Ut ſe erigat claviculis ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is quaſi ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus, &amp;c. <hi>Cicero.</hi> Adeo ramos ſtring it, ut craſſe ſcere prohibeat. <hi>Scal.</hi>
               </note> that it may be ſuſtained thereby: Thus we, being ſenſible of our owne frailty, ſhould apprehend the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious promiſes and rich mercies of Almighty God, and adhere unto Chriſt by a lively faith.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.26.</note> 
               <hi>Jacob</hi> would not let the Angel goe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept he bleſt him: ſo we by applying the merits of our Redeemer unto our ſoules, doe receive a bleſſing from the Lord. When wee doe tie our ſelves unto our Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atour
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:176251:115"/>by the cords of love, (which is the bond of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectneſſe) as a Sacrifice unto the Altar, we ſhall be kept from falling, and the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent ſhall not have power to fold himſelfe about us, who are ſo neerely united to our heavenly Father. The Vine-tree is not fit for any uſe but onely to beare fruit: ſhall wood be taken there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to doe any work? or will men take a pin of it to hang any veſſell thereon?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 15.3.</note> An unfruitfull Chriſtian is the moſt unprofitable creature that is; a heavie burthen to the earth, a cumbrance to the ground, no better than the wild gourds in the pot, a vexation to the righteous ſoule, and a ſtumbling block to the wicked.</p>
            <pb n="217" facs="tcp:176251:115"/>
            <p> Other trees may beare fruit upon the young ſprigs that did ſhoot out in the former yeere; but this doth exceed them all, bringing forth grapes upon the new bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, in the ſame yeere in which they did proceed from the body of the Vine: thereby teaching us even in the very beginning of our profeſſion to become fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and profitable in our converſation, running the waies of Gods Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 119.32.60.</note> and without delay making haſte to keep his Statutes.</p>
            <p>How can they that have neglected ſo great ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and deferred to returne unto the Lord, expect that he ſhould heare them, when in affliction they ſeeke him
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:176251:116"/>early (ſeeming fervent in prayer when they firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to call upon his Name) and cry unto him, O God make ſpeed to ſave us, O Lord make haſte to help us, whereas they during their whole life, it may be theſe forty yeers long, have grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the good Spirit, and er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in their hearts, putting the evill day of Gods judgement, and the good day of true repentance far from them? But there is fruit of a better relliſh to be gathered from the Vine; if that be prevented by the froſt,
<note place="margin">Gelatione cohibita, in ſequenti anno du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plum dabit. <hi>Scal. in Theop.</hi>
               </note> and hindred from bearing one yeere, in the following yeere it will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence that loſſe by a twofold reſtitution. If we have been as trees without
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:176251:116"/>fruit, we muſt not ſtill per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in impiety, and live to the luſts of men, but labour to redeem the time, by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounding alwaies in the worke of the Lord; that as <hi>Ahimaaz,</hi> over-ran <hi>Cuſhi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.23.</note> who was ſent before him; ſo we may ſupply by our diligence and chearfull obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience what was wanting in time: And as Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> who was laſt called,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.5.</note> was not a whit behind the very chiefeſt Apoſtles; ſo we in ſpirituall endowments and glorious reward may bee made equall unto them, who entred the worke be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our ſelves. Where the fruit of this tree is moſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed,
<note place="margin">In agro Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reliano vina excellentiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſima; Nulla vinea vetula, ſed &amp;c. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </note> they doe not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer any old Vines to grow, but repleniſh the ground
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:176251:117"/>with new, whoſe fruit is moſt acceptable; thereby teaching us to put off the old man, and to be renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in our mind, putting on the new man,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.23.</note> which after God is created in righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe and true holineſſe. The Lord ſatisfieth our mouth with good things,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.5.</note> ſo that our youth is renewed like the Eagles: And the Lord ſatisfieth our ſoule with his mercy, ſo that his graces are revived and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired in us by the worke of the quickning Spirit;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 2.8.</note> He turned the water into wine at the marriage of Cana in Galile; and hee ſends the comfortable ſhowers,
<note place="margin">Initia vini eſſe aquea. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </note> that doe moiſten and cheriſh the roots of the Vine, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them to produce their
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:176251:117"/>fruit, in which there is a bleſſing; Hee turneth our ſorrow into joy,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.8.</note> our weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into rejoycing;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 16.20.</note> He ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the barren woman to be a joyfull mother of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; and hee maketh the barren heart to bring forth the fruit of the Spirit,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 113.</note> and giveth wiſedome and all heavenly bleſſings liberal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, above that which wee can aske or thinke; Our lot is falne to us in a good ground, we are planted in a fertile ſoile, we receive the beſt gifts from the open hand of a bountifull Father. Now as the Vine doth draw much vertue and nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment out of the earth,
<note place="margin">Neceſſe eſt eam multum quoque tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </note> that it may produce abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of goodly cluſters, and great plenty of large
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:176251:118"/>leaves, and long branches; ſo we ſhould derive much ſtrength and power from that fulneſſe which is in Chriſt, that wee may bee complete, and furniſhed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to every good worke; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fitted to performe any holy duty, being prepared to ſuffer any triall or afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which the Lord ſhall be pleaſed to impoſe upon us: As upon the Vine there be great ſtore of grapes joyned together in one cluſter; ſo in the ſoule of a Chriſtian there ſhould be all kinds of graces accumulate and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped together, in ſtead of that maſſe of ſin and lump of corruption, which wee brought into this world: Wee ſhould be filled with all knowledge, and all joy,
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:176251:118"/>and peace in beleeving; we ſhould be full of goodneſſe, ready to communicate, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to diſtribute to the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of other men: Which workes of charity, and all other pious actions, are like the fruit of the Vine; for as wee have the comfortable uſe and benefit of that, a long time after it hath been trodden in the wine-preſſe; ſo likewiſe, of Gods free grace wee doe receive the reward of the good things done in our body after our diſſolution; and doe then drinke the cup of ſalvation, when wee enter into our Maſters joy, and are deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered from all weakneſſe in the body, and infirmity in the ſoule; from all inward and outward frailties, even
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:176251:119"/>as the grapes in the wine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe are freed and cleared both from the huskes and kernels: Such is our cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption and imperfection here in this world, that our beſt performances are pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted by the contagion of ſinne dwelling in our mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and may in that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard bee likened to theſe grapes, or or other fruits, which have either ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing without to bee pared off, and caſt away, or elſe ſome coare, ſtone, or ker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell within to be rejected. In our moſt devout exerciſes, and godly endeavours, there is either ſome defect and errour to be diſcerned by man, who lookes to the outward appearance; or though wee ſhould bee
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:176251:119"/>blameleſſe before man, yet there is ſome inward rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion and iniquity, that is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and manifeſt before the Lord, who looketh to the heart. When we are ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of our former exceſſe and ſuperfluity, and are caſt downe in acknowledgment of our tranſgreſſions, wee ſhould not thereby be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terred from continuance in well-doing; but rather ſeek to amend that in which we have failed, and gone out of the way; that as ſuch fruits are eſteemed beſt (in their kinds) in which there is the leaſt waſte,
<note place="margin">Molluſca, quod caeteris nucibus mollior ſit. <hi>Macrob.</hi>
               </note> either in the ſhell, or any other part that is unprofitable; ſo our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances may be moſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable, when they are not defiled by any groſſe er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:176251:120"/>or preſumptuous ſinne. The Lord,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.12.</note> who is able to purge the wheat from the chaffe, will approve of our good endeavours and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſires, being the fruit of the Spirit; and will be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to pardon our ſwerving and deadneſſe, which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from the bitter root of a deceitfull heart.</p>
            <p>In divers of our fruits there is ſome kernell, that being ſowne doth grow up in ſuch a plant, as may bring forth more fruit of the ſame kind; in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, the end of one good action ſhould be the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of another: we ſhould labour to increaſe and mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply in heavenly graces, and ſpirituall gifts, and our reward ſhal be great in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven;
<pb n="227" facs="tcp:176251:120"/>For unto us it ſhall be given to eate of the Tree of life,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Revel.</hi> 2.7. &amp; 22.2.</note> which is in the middeſt of the Paradiſe of God: A tree that bears twelve man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of fruits, and yeelds her fruit every moneth: Such fruit as doth for ever ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt us from the dominion of death; ſuch fruit as doth open our eyes, for we ſhall ſee God face to face;
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.12.</note> ſuch fruit as doth make us to be as gods, wee ſhall bee like him,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>John</hi> 3.2.</note> for wee ſhall ſee him as hee is; ſuch fruit as is good for food, ſo very good,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa</hi> 49.10.</note> that when we taſte thereof, wee ſhall never hunger any more,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 6.34.</note> nor thirſt any more: But as the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciple ſaid, <hi>Lord, evermore give us this bread;</hi> ſo wee ſhall alwaies deſire, and for
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:176251:121"/>ever enjoy this food that endures in everlaſting life: Such fruit as is pleaſant to the eye;
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.9.</note> for ſince the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the world, the eye hath not ſeen the things which God hath prepared for them that love him; Such fruit as is to be deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to make one wiſe, even wiſe unto ſalvation; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which all the wiſdome of this world is fooliſhneſs, and enmity againſt God: But this wiſedome is a Tree of life to them that lay hold upon her;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 3.18. &amp; 4.9.</note> a Crown of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſhall ſhe deliver to them. Did our firſt parents think that the fruit of the tree of Knowledge was to be deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.6.</note> when it was forbidden? And ſhall we by a ſtronger deluſion beleeve that this
<pb n="229" facs="tcp:176251:121"/>fruit of the Tree of Life is to be neglected and avoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, when wee are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to labour for it? All the trees in the garden of Eden could not ſatisfie them, but they would eate of the forbidden fruit, though they became ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the curſe thereby. The abundant variety of all the precious fruits brought forth by the Sunne, ſhould not pleaſe nor content us, without this bleſſed fruit of the Tree of Life. <hi>Adam</hi> was prevented, that hee might not put forth his hand to take of that Tree, leſt having eaten unworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, hee deceived himſelfe with a vaine hope of life, when death ſhould ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly overtake him; But wee
<pb n="230" facs="tcp:176251:122"/>have time and liberty gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto us, that we may ſtretch forth the hand of faith, and receive this fruit, whereof if wee eate, wee ſhall not dye; He might not gather it upon earth, but we may receive it from heaven. The Manna, which was kept untill the holy Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, had no worme in it: If wee now treaſure up this good fruit againſt the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath of Reſt for our ſoules, it ſhall never be taken away from us; Hee that gathers little, ſhall have no lacke: But if in this day of ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on we gather great plenty thereof, we may then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently ſay, Soule, take thy reſt for evermore, thou haſt much goods laid up for all eternity.</p>
            <pb n="231" facs="tcp:176251:122"/>
            <p> The Tree of Life is in the middeſt of the Paradiſe of God: Oh that the fruit thereof were hidden in our inward parts, that we could lay it up, and keep it in our hearts! wee would then e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem all the dignities and delights in the world to be of as ſhort continuance,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.4. Ita in mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſcit. <hi>Plaut.</hi>
               </note> as the haſty fruit before the Summer, which when hee that looketh upon it ſeeth it, while it is yet in his hand he eateth it up; And to be no better than that fruit, which was ſtollen out of the Orchard,
<note place="margin">Non erant formâ, nec ſapore ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cebroſa.</note> that had nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther forme to catch the eye, nor relliſh to allure the hand; For which that bleſſed man in his repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance paid the deareſt price that ever was paid for any
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:176251:123"/>fruit, which was eaten by any of the ſonnes of <hi>Adam.</hi> We give fruit unto froward children, that they may for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake that which is of more value; Shall wee bee ſuch children in underſtanding, for the trifling vanities of this life, to reject the dura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble riches of the heavenly Kingdome? Shall wee for the three Apples of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,
<note place="margin">Atalanta, ſive Lucrum. <hi>Bacon Sap. Vet.</hi> Victa curſu dum malis tribus colli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendis retar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>data. <hi>Nat. Com.</hi>
               </note> pleaſure, and profit, which are caſt before us, be ſtopped in our race, and ſo loſe an incorruptible Crowne, an eternall weight of glory? The commodities of this world may ſeem to be like the fruits about the dead ſea, delectable to the eye as Apples of gold; but being touched, they fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to aſhes: when we thinke to
<pb n="233" facs="tcp:176251:123"/>take ſureſt hold of them, they deceive us. Wee are not like the Caduſians,
<note place="margin">Plutar.</note> who were a ſtrong people, and yet fed upon nothing but Apples and Peares, and ſuch like fruit; from theſe we receive the leaſt part of our nouriſhment: So like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe all outward benefits doe not conduce to our true happineſſe, unleſſe wee uſe them as we ſometimes uſe our fruit, to procure an appetite unto that which is more ſolid; So we by ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of the Lords bounty in theſe externall bleſſings, ſhould be excited to hunger after Righteouſneſſe, and the ſpirituall food of our ſoules, that we ſo we may be abundantly ſatisfied with the fatneſſe of Gods houſe,
<pb n="234" facs="tcp:176251:124"/>and may drinke of the river of his pleaſures for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</p>
            <p>Now, as the induſtrious Bee doth gather honey, not only from the bloſſomes which are upon the trees, but alſo from the flowers which grow upon the earth; ſo wee, having for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly laboured to receive inſtruction from the trees, will now endeavour to take ſome permanent benefit from the fading flowers. I will not inſiſt upon the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe of them, who are worthy to be blamed for their violent deſire, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in all kind of ſtrange novelties;
<note place="margin">Quorum literae in Thraciam, Graeciam, Indiam diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currunt. <hi>Lipſ.</hi>
               </note> whoſe letters are ſent into remote parts of the world, for ſome ſmall ſeed, or root, which they
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:176251:124"/>cheriſh as the mother doth the childe;
<note place="margin">Quib. aegri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us fit florem aliquem no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vum mori, quam &amp;c. <hi>Idem.</hi>
               </note> and grieve more for the death of a new flower, than of an old friend. Wee know, that <hi>Adam</hi> in Paradiſe was foiled, whereas <hi>Job</hi> ſitting among the aſhes did over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Tempter. There is offence by vanity and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluity, when wee ſeeke wholly to pleaſe the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſenſes of the body, and doe never project how to ſtrengthen the inward powers and faculties of the ſoule: Which errour wee will now reforme, hoping by our paines and diligence herein, wee may recover ſome part of that excellent happineſſe of our firſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, rather than be driven further off from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable
<pb n="236" facs="tcp:176251:125"/>fruition of true fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitie.</p>
            <p>Firſt then we doe admire and adore the wiſedome and power of Almighty God, whoſe hands have made all theſe things. Who can behold the Sunne and Moone, and all the Starres of light, but he muſt with all reverence acknowledge the glory of God, which is declared by them? and who can view and obſerve the rare beauty and riches of the earth, but he muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the excellent perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that is ſeene in them? There was no more ſpirit in the Queene of Sheba when ſhee beheld the ſtate and pomp of <hi>Solomon;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 10.5.</note> and yet even <hi>Solomon</hi> in all his glory was not arrayed like one Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 6.29.</note>
               <pb n="237" facs="tcp:176251:125"/>That goodneſſe and providence of God which doth ſhine forth in one flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, doth exceed the greateſt roialty of that moſt magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent King.
<note place="margin">Liliorum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptio vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur aptiſsimè convenire, &amp;c. <hi>Flamin.</hi>
               </note> The ſame word in the inſcription of the Pſalm is expounded either of the Lilies, or of the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of ſix ſtrings: As the ſound of thoſe Inſtruments, ſo the ſixe leaves of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie may excite us to praiſe the name of the Lord.
<note place="margin">Immiſcens varios natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra colores. <hi>Sincer.</hi> Parthica quae tantis varian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur cingula gemmis? <hi>Claudian.</hi>
               </note> If this one flower be arrayed in this manner, then what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable luſtre and ſplendour is in that rich war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drobe when it is brought forth? With what won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull variety of colours is the earth enamelled? What ſumptuous robe of the moſt mighty Potentate may be
<pb n="236" facs="tcp:176251:126"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="237" facs="tcp:176251:126"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="238" facs="tcp:176251:127"/>compared to this raiment of divers colours, wherewith this terreſtriall globe is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorned?
<note place="margin">Alba vere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundis Lilia pinge Roſis. <hi>Sincer.</hi> Lilia prato candida. <hi>Propert.</hi> Et Roſa pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pureo creſcit rubicunda colore. <hi>Virg.</hi> Sanguineo ſplendore Roſas. <hi>Claud.</hi>
               </note> The Lilies excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding white as ſnow, ſo as no Fuller on earth can white them; the Roſes of ſuch an abſolute and perfect red, that the moſt exact imitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by art, is no better than <hi>Joſephs</hi> coat dipped in the bloud of the Kid, if com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared thereunto:
<note place="margin">Et dulce Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olas ferrugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne pingit. <hi>Claud.</hi>
               </note> the Violet, whoſe grave and ſtately colour doth ſurpaſſe the Purple of the rich man; the Tulippa, and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, whoſe yellow is to be preferred before the cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which was made of wrought gold; And beſides this preheminence of the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, wherein there is great
<pb n="239" facs="tcp:176251:127"/>diverſity in the ſame kinds, let us conſider the differing ſhapes and proportions in which they grow, the times and ſeaſons in which ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſively they blow and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen themſelves, that wee may never want the aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant choice of fragrant o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours, and ſweet ſavours, that moſt of them doe caſt abroad:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.24.</note> And we cannot for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare to ſay with <hi>David, O Lord how manifold are thy workes! in wiſedome haſt thou made them all; the earth is full of thy riches.</hi> If the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall power and goodneſſe of God be made manifeſt in theſe things that are of leaſt continuance, then how much more in the durable riches that are provided for us? If ſuch beauty be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred
<pb n="240" facs="tcp:176251:128"/>upon a fading flower,
<note place="margin">Cujus rei in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniri poteſt brevior ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas: <hi>Quintil.</hi>
               </note> then what unſpeakeable glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is reſerved in the heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Kingdome? If ſuch ſweetneſſe may be found in theſe things which ſpring out of the earth, then what ſolace may be received by the good gifts that deſcend from above? If ſuch com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts here in this life, what pleaſures for evermore at the right hand of God? If while the King ſitteth at his table, the Spouſes ſpikenard ſendeth forth the ſmell thereof, and he be unto her as a bundle of myrrhe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant</hi> 1.12.</note> and a cluſter of Cypres; If Chriſt being abſent doth impart and communicate ſuch bleſſings unto us, now in our pilgrimage, by the Word and Spirit, then what
<pb n="241" facs="tcp:176251:128"/>fulneſſe of joy will there be when we appeare with him in glory? As we are deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the ſmell of ſweet herbes and flowers, when they are compoſed in one bundle; ſo God is well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with the plenteous varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ſundry graces in a true beleever: and then doe we offer up a ſweet odour, an acceptable ſacrifice unto the Lord.</p>
            <p>In the Scripture flowers are frequently named to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe our fraile eſtate here in this world: <hi>Job</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi> 14.2.</note> 
               <hi>Man commeth forth like a flower, and is cut downe. David</hi> ſaith, <hi>As a flower of the field,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.15.</note> 
               <hi>ſo man flouriſheth: the wind paſſeth over it, and it is gone.</hi> Saint <hi>James</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.11.</note> 
               <hi>The Sun is no ſooner riſen with a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="242" facs="tcp:176251:129"/>heat, but the flower fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, and the grace of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion of it periſheth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 28.4.</note> 
               <hi>The glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious beauty of Ephraim ſhalbe a fading flower,</hi> ſaith the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Eſay:</hi> &amp; in another place he ſaith,
<note place="margin">&amp; 40.6.</note> that <hi>the goodlineſſe of all fleſh is as the flower that fadeth;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.25. Purpureus veluti cum flos ſucciſus aratro Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueſcit mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riens. <hi>Virg.</hi> Pubenteſque roſae primos moriuntur ad Auſtros. <hi>Statius.</hi> Ut cum ſole malo triſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que roſaria pallent Uſta Noto. <hi>Idem.</hi> Alioqui tu illos in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuſtatem re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervabas, &amp;c. <hi>Quintil.</hi>
               </note> And Saint <hi>Peter</hi> (as it is probable) alluding to that place, confirmes the ſame truth, that <hi>the glory of man is as the flower that fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth away.</hi> All outward gifts and endowments are as flowers, long in planting, and cheriſhing, and growing up, but ſhort in enjoying the ſweetneſſe of them. Wee may as well reſolve to keep our flowers continually freſh and beautifull, as to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect any conſtant poſſeſſion of the tranſitory benefits of
<pb n="243" facs="tcp:176251:129"/>this world.
<note place="margin">Floribus tam diu gratis donec re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centibus. <hi>Sidon.</hi>
               </note> Wherefore let us uſe them as we doe our flowers, which doe pleaſe us well while they be freſh, but wee caſt them away when wee have had the ſweetneſſe of them: So long as theſe outward comforts are helpfull unto us, and doe excite us to praiſe and thankſgiving, we may ſafely uſe them; but when they come to be liveleſſe and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effectuall, we ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce them.</p>
            <p>Such are the commodities of this life, and ſuch is our life it ſelfe; it is even a va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pour that appeareth for a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle time,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam</hi> 4.14.</note> and then vaniſheth away. The longeſt life that ever any man lived, was not ſo much as one day in Gods account.
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.8.</note> How many doe
<pb n="244" facs="tcp:176251:130"/>wither away before they be growne up?
<note place="margin">Qualem vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gineo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſſum pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice florem, Cuineque fulgor adhuc nec dum ſua forma receſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit. <hi>Virg.</hi>
               </note> How many are gathered in the flower of their youth, in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of beauty and ſtrength? Even as ſoone as the Sunne is riſen, and ſhines upon them, they fade away: Or if we doe beare the heat of the day, yet when the evening of old age is come, like our flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Peru,
<note place="margin">Una dies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perit, confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit una dies.</note> wee then fall to the ground.</p>
            <p>In regard of the brevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of our time wee may change that ſpeech of <hi>Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dad,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi> 8.9.</note> 
               <hi>We are but of yeſterday, and know nothing:</hi> Wee need not goe ſo farre as he did; for we may ſay, We are but of this day, and know nothing; and which is the greateſt miſery in this
<pb n="245" facs="tcp:176251:130"/>our ignorance, we care not to know or conſider the ſhortneſſe of our lives; We know not that <hi>Adam</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode one day in the ſtate of knowledge before he fell; we know that we ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue one day in this ſtate of ignorance before wee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to the duſt. The wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked cannot hope for length of dayes, but rather to be ſnared ſuddenly in an evill time,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9.12.</note> when it fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth ſuddenly upon them. The godly doe neither ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect nor deſire long life:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.38.</note> the world is not worthy of ſuch who are the Lords Jewels,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.17. Oſtentatus raptuſque ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mul, ſolſtitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis velut her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba ſolet. <hi>Auſon.</hi>
               </note> which hee brings forth, and ſhewes them to the people, and then makes them up againe. If our ſtay be ſo ſhort, it
<pb n="246" facs="tcp:176251:131"/>behoves us ever to bee prepared for our end, and with Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to dye daily, in our readineſſe to be diſſolved. In this our latter giving our ſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord, in commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding our ſpirits into the hands of our Father, God loveth a cheerefull giver; we muſt not do it grudging<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<note place="margin">Abeamque ex hac vita, non ut eje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus, ſed ut e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſus. <hi>Lipſ.</hi>
               </note> or of neceſſitie, but with a willing mind. The Lord of the Vineyard, as he hath power to ſend la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers into the worke at what houre he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, ſo hee hath power to call them from their worke at what houre hee thinks good. Bleſſed are they that die in the Lord, for they reſt from their labours, and their workes
<pb n="247" facs="tcp:176251:131"/>follow them; To ſuch to live is Chriſt, and to dye is gaine. Better is that Roſe which is gathered in the bud,
<note place="margin">Ecce &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluxit rutili coma punica floris, Dum loquor &amp; tellus tecta rubore mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat. <hi>Auſon.</hi>
               </note> that an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent water may be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilled from it, than that which hangs longer, and at laſt falls to the earth without any uſe or benefit. Better is the ſhort race of the faithfull man, whoſe good name is as precious ointment that filleth the houſe with the ſweet o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour, than the long reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the ungodly, who are not profitable ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in life or death.</p>
            <p>Having mentioned the Roſe,
<note place="margin">Roſeus color a principe florum. <hi>Scal. Exer.</hi>
               </note> the Prince of flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, it will not be imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent to extract the ſpirit thereof, to trie what ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue
<pb n="248" facs="tcp:176251:132"/>wee may draw from the ſame: When we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Roſe growing upon a Brier, wee may againe call to remembrance that curſe denounced in the beginning, Thornes and thiſtles ſhall the earth bring forth to thee; Wee may thinke upon our ſinne, which did provoke the Lord to inflict that puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And then from the colour of this flower wee may learne to take ſhame unto our ſelves,
<note place="margin">Extremus roſeo pudor errat in ore. <hi>Val. Flac. Gen.</hi> 2.25.</note> which is one of the attendants of ſinne; for in the eſtate of Innocencie, <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> though naked, yet were not aſhamed.</p>
            <p>Being thus caſt downe in ſenſe of our unworthineſſe, we muſt ſeeke for mercy
<pb n="249" facs="tcp:176251:132"/>through the merits of Chriſt, who became ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject unto the curſe, and was rent and wounded by the thornes that were fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtened unto him; Who in his reſurrection was the Roſe of Sharon, full of grace and majeſty, bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſweet conſolation unto all that approach nigh un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him by faith; Through his favour the malediction is turned into a bleſſing, and we may receive much delight and comfort by the uſe of this excellent flower; yet alwaies re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring that the way to Heaven is not ſtrowne with Roſes and Violets, with delicacies and pleaſures: For although we have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward peace and joy, wee
<pb n="250" facs="tcp:176251:133"/>muſt meet with many af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, and ſuffer mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold tribulations, before wee can enter into the Kingdom of Heaven. They would pull a Roſe without prickes, who would em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace a godly life, without oppoſition and enmity from the world.</p>
            <p>As the Roſe doth teach us modeſty; ſo the Violet humility: which doth not lift up it ſelfe, like the empty eares of corne; or like the Bramble in the Parable,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Judg.</hi> 9.</note> that other trees may come under the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of it: but in all low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe adheres to the earth that gives nouriſhment thereunto.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi> 37.18.</note> 
               <hi>Elihu</hi> ſaith, God hath ſpread out the skie, which is ſtrong, and as a
<pb n="251" facs="tcp:176251:133"/>molten looking-glaſſe: In that glaſſe we may ſee the lively colour of the Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let, and may obſerve, that the right way to true ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour is by humility:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 15.33.</note> They that have learned to hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble themſelves, ſhall in due time be exalted. The former colour of the Roſe,
<note place="margin">Vel miſta rubent ubi Lilia multa Alba Roſa, &amp;c. <hi>Virg.</hi>
               </note> this of the Violet, and that of the Lilie, are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed the three chiefe ingredients in beauty: Where there is ſhame for their former diſobedience and other ſinnes,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.14.</note> whereof they have been guilty; and true humility in the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement of their unworthineſſe and imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.21.</note> and an holy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to keep themſelves pure, and without blemiſh
<pb n="252" facs="tcp:176251:134"/>for the time to come. Thoſe ſoules are all glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious within, they are all faire like the Spouſe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 47.</note> and there is no ſpot in them. If wee could find a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript, how our bodies, which are as the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments unto the ſoule in this our pilgrimage, may endure in the prime beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, like the clothes of the Iſraelites in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.5.</note> which did not waxe old upon them; how our youth might bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed like the Eagles,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.5.</note> and we may continue untill our latter end in perfect come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, not having our beſt forme obſcured by the wrinkles of age; there bee very many who would rejoyce herein, more than
<pb n="253" facs="tcp:176251:134"/>he doth that finds a great treaſure: And ſuch a Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician as could thus helpe them, ſhould bee liberal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly paid, though they did endure many dayes tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to gaine this harme and loſſe. Now, which is much more, here is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently ſet before us an approved experiment, Not how to retaine our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer favour; but how to increaſe more and more in divine beauty, and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent lovelineſſe, by wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing in the bloud of that immaculate Lambe, and by being adorned with the graces of the holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that wee may bee as the Sunne when hee go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth forth in his might,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Judg.</hi> 5.31.</note> which doth not reveale
<pb n="254" facs="tcp:176251:135"/>its complete majeſtie, when it firſt comes out at the doore of the Tabernacle, but after aſcends to great glory: Though our begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings bee weake, yet we ſhall attaine unto a more perfect eſtate: And as <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> eye was not dimme,
<note place="margin">Neque au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fugit Viror ejus. <hi>Calvin.</hi> Viriditas ejus. <hi>Jun.</hi>
               </note> nor his naturall force abated when hee died, but was then as greene and flouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing as in former time; ſo we in old age, and in death it ſelfe ſhall ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the vigour of the new man, which after God is created in righteouſneſſe and true holineſſe; And after our diſſolution the ſoule ſhall appeare in glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, as the lamps in <hi>Gide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> Army did then ſhine forth, when the pitchers
<pb n="255" facs="tcp:176251:135"/>were broken. Though for the preſent this divine Light bee eclipſed by the interpoſition of the body of the earth; yet at the laſt day the body alſo ſhall become ſpirituall, and we ſhall put on, not rich robes and coſtly array, not pearles and flowers, and ſuch like ornaments;
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.53.</note> but Incorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Immortality;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.21.</note> And our body ſhall be faſhio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned like the glorious bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of Chriſt; That is the laſt and laſting faſhion; the faſhion that will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low all other: Oh that all other would follow that faſhion, that we would labour for holineſſe; And ſo being eſpouſed unto one husband,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2.</note> we may be preſented to Chriſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="256" facs="tcp:176251:136"/>ſpot or wrinkle,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.27.</note> or any ſuch thing; As a chaſte Virgin, caring for the things of the Lord, that ſhee may bee holy both in body and ſpirit.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.34.</note>
            </p>
            <p>I doe not deny, that divers ornaments are to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable, and there may be ſome diſtinction and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, according to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and dignity: The Crowne that is fit to bee ſet upon the head, is not meet to bee placed upon any other part of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die: But there muſt bee abſtinence in ſome things,
<note place="margin">Non tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum medio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critas co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenda eſt, ſed etiam abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentia. <hi>Calv.</hi>
               </note> and moderation in all. Such as are captivated by their owne chaines, ſuch as are inthralled by fond affecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and notorious oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, ſhould breake thoſe
<pb n="257" facs="tcp:176251:136"/>bands aſunder, and caſt away their fetters from them: Shall wee with the Phariſee looke only to the out-ſide, which may bee like a painted Sepulchre? Shall they that profeſſe themſelves to bee Gods ſervants, bee of as little uſe in the Church, as is commonly made of the Tulippa in the garden, which is onely for ſhew? And yet even by viewing of that various flower, we may obſerve ſomething that may bee helpfull un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us: For as that fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, and the grace of it periſheth; ſo ſhall the rich man, clothed in goodly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parrell and fine linnen,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.11.</note> fade away in his waies; Yea, ſo ſhall the faſhion of this
<pb n="258" facs="tcp:176251:137"/>world paſſe away,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.31.</note> and the luſt thereof; but hee that doth the will of God abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth for ever:
<note place="margin">1 <hi>John</hi> 2.17.</note> Hee ſhall live an eternall felicitie; And may in that regard bee compared unto this flower, which in Winter ſhrinkes low into the earth, but in the Spring doth riſe againe with great beauty; ſo although for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent he may be caſt downe in godly ſorrow for his ſinnes, yet hee ſhall bee lifted up with comfort and conſolation, when the Sunne of Righteouſneſſe ſhall ariſe with healing in his wings, and ſhine upon him with grace and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour.</p>
            <p>Then let us learne of this and other flowers,
<pb n="259" facs="tcp:176251:137"/>which doe open them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,
<note place="margin">Helotro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pium, &amp;c.</note> and turne towards the Sunne when it ſhines upon them, that they may bee refreſhed by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence thereof; to open unto Chriſt, that he may enter into our ſoules; to encline our eares unto his Word, and our hearts to keep his Commandements; And to turne unto the Lord with all our ſtrength, that wee may bee enligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tened by his glorious truth, and ſupported by his al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty power.</p>
            <p>The Word of God is as ſeed ſowne in our hearts; it may be, wee have for a long time been unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable hearers, and the Word wee have received hath been as the ſeed of
<pb n="260" facs="tcp:176251:138"/>this flower before named, which doth not ſatisfie our deſire, untill many yeeres after it is ſowne: Yet let it not for ever bee buried within us; for then it will prove the ſavour of death unto death:
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.16.</note> but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther let it bee as the ſeed wee ſow,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.36.</note> which firſt dies, and then is quickened.</p>
            <p>That ſeed which fell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong ſtony places ſprung up forthwith,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.</note> and was as ſuddenly ſcorched: If this ſeed hath for a great ſpace been hid within us, let it take the deeper root, and at laſt bring forth an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred fold. Doth the earth bring forth herbes meet for them by whom it is dreſſed?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.7.</note> Doth the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den cauſe the things that
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.11.</note>
               <pb n="261" facs="tcp:176251:138"/>are ſowne in it to ſpring forth? And ſhall not man,
<note place="margin">Terra nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſat imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, nec un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam ſine uſurâ reddit quod acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit, &amp;c. <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cero.</hi>
               </note> who receives theſe bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of the fatneſſe of the earth, become fruitfull himſelfe, that hee may likewiſe bee bleſſed with all heavenly bleſſings in ſpirituall places in Jeſus Chriſt?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.7.</note> Doth man (for the moſt part) Doth man (for the moſt part) reap what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever hee ſoweth? and ſhall God reape nothing but tares, having ſowne ſuch precious ſeed? Shall the good things commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto us produce ſuch bad effects, like unto the wheat that is ſowne,
<note place="margin">Infoelix lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium &amp; ſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantur ave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae.</note> which in a barren yeere doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate into darnell? Far bee it from us to requite the Lord in this manner: If hee call, and wee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe;
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:176251:139"/>If hee ſtretch out his hand, and wee regard not, then hee will laugh at our calamity, and wee ſhall call upon him, but hee will not heare; wee ſhall ſeeke him early, but ſhall not find him: but if wee doe hearken to his Word, and obey his voice, then our prayers ſhall come up as a memoriall before God, and bee as ſeed ſowne, not in the earth beneath, but in heaven a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, and ſhall cauſe a rich and plentifull increaſe of all heavenly bleſſings to come downe upon us, that our ſoules may bee filled with good things: Yea, then our workes of charity, and all godly acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſhall be as ſeed which
<pb n="263" facs="tcp:176251:139"/>we caſt abroad, and ſow to the Spirit,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.8.</note> that of the Spirit wee may reap life everlaſting:
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.6.</note> 
               <hi>Hee that ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſparingly, ſhall reape ſparingly; and hee that ſoweth bountifully, ſhall reap bountifully.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 11.25.</note> The liberall ſoule ſhall bee made fat, and he that watereth, ſhall be alſo watered himſelfe. Dare wee truſt the earth with our ſeed? and dare wee not truſt our faithfull Creatour in theſe workes of charity?</p>
            <p>The earth hath no pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er nor ſufficiencie in it felfe, but only from his benedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; Shall wee doubt of his goodneſſe and mercy, who is moſt juſt and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous in himſelfe, and who doth give this fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity
<pb n="264" facs="tcp:176251:140"/>and ability unto the earth, that it may make an abundant returne of that wherewith it is tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted? Are wee of ſuch little faith? And doe we thus feare in diſpencing theſe outward commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, theſe tranſitory be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits? Then how ſhall wee bee able to commend our ſpirit into the hands of our Father? With what courage and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort ſhall we commit our bodies to the earth (being the laſt ſeed we doe ſow) which ſhall bee raiſed in power and great glory, excelling that of the pure Lillie, more than that doth the royaltie of <hi>Solomon?</hi> Awake and ſing yee that dwell in duſt; for thy dew
<pb n="265" facs="tcp:176251:140"/>is as the dew of herbes, and the earth ſhall caſt out the dead.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.19. &amp; 11.1. In illo loco Meſsias ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur Flos; &amp; conſentit Hieronymus. <hi>Cauſabon. Job</hi> 38.27.</note> The Flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the ſtemme of <hi>Jeſſe</hi> did ſpring up in a gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and our graves ſhall bee turned into garden-plots. As the raine cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the bud of the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der herbe to ſpring up; ſo the Lord is able to raiſe us up unto eternall joy and felicity; Yea in this firſt reſurrection hee doth raiſe us up from the death of ſinne, to the life of grace: I will bee as the dew unto Iſrael,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14.5.</note> even as the cloud of dew in the heare of harveſt.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 18.4.</note> God makes the ſmall drops of water; they powre downe raine according to the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pour thereof, which the
<pb n="266" facs="tcp:176251:141"/>clouds doe drop and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtill upon man aboundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi> 36.27.</note> to ſatisfie the deſolate and waſte ground.</p>
            <p>In like manner he doth ſendus the ſhowers of his grace, he gives us the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of all ſpirituall gifts, he doth refreſh us with his favour, and ſatisfie our thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty ſoules with his loving kindneſſe. <hi>Apollo's</hi> wate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring is to ſmall effect, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe God gives his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 11.10.</note> Although the ſeed we ſow may grow when we water it with our foot, yet the ſeed of grace in our hearts can never proſper, unleſſe the Sonne of man, who began that good work, doth likewiſe perfect the ſame.</p>
            <p>When the ſweet and
<pb n="267" facs="tcp:176251:141"/>comfortable ſhowers doe fall upon the earth, they doe not onely cheriſh the flowers and herbs, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo doe occaſion many of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive weeds readily to grow up: ſo the good gifts that come downe from the Father of lights, the gracious bleſſings that deſcend from above, doe bring forth the acceptable fruit of praiſe and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience in the godly, but the curſed weeds of rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion and provocation in the wicked. The goodneſſe of God, which, as a gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſhower mollifying the drie earth, doth leade the humble ſoule to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; but doth harden the impenitent heart, which is fully ſet to doe evill, and
<pb n="268" facs="tcp:176251:142"/>to treaſure up wrath againſt the day of wrath. The Word of God, in ſeaſon like the former, and out of ſeaſon like the latter raine, is the true bread that comes downe from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and doth refreſh him that is weary and ready to faint, and doth ſatisfie him that is hungry, that he ſhall never hunger any more; but it cauſeth loa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the full ſoule; As the Iſraelites did not find any ſweetneſſe or good reliſh in the ſpirituall meat, the food of Angels,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.3. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ.</hi> 78.24, 25.</note> the corne of heaven that God rained downe upon them: Our ſoule is dried away, there is nothing at all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides this Manna before our eyes:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Num.</hi> 11.6.</note> Here is Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,
<pb n="269" facs="tcp:176251:142"/>and Manna, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Manna: they called it light bread,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Num.</hi> 21.5.</note> and as lightly they eſteemed of it.</p>
            <p>Thus the naturall man receiveth not the things of the ſpirit of God,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14.</note> for they are fooliſhneſſe unto him; neither can he know them, becauſe they are ſpiritually diſcerned: hee cannot apprehend the live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly power of the hidden Manna;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.17.</note> he cannot diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the ſecret of the Lord, which is revealed unto them that feare his name. The tares that appeared in the field were ſuffered to grow unto the harveſt;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.30.</note> but the weeds that come up in the garden muſt bee taken away in the
<pb n="270" facs="tcp:176251:143"/>very beginning; Our vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces muſt be plucked up by the roots before they bee ſurely fixed by long continuance.
<note place="margin">Abdolony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus hortum, malas herbas eligens, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purgabat. <hi>Q. Curt.</hi>
               </note> The Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian makes mention of a Gardiner who was found deſtroying of bad weeds, when <hi>Alexander</hi> ſent for him, and advanced him to a kingdome: So wee, ſupplanting our corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and caſting out the unfruitfull workes of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſhall attaine to a crowne of life. As <hi>Adam</hi> was to dreſſe the Garden of Eden, ſo wee are to keepe our ſoule and body blameleſſe from the pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of ſinne: and in the end, when wee reſt from our labour, we ſhall enter into our Maſters joy.
<pb n="271" facs="tcp:176251:143"/>Chriſt ſaith to the good Theefe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 23.43.</note> 
               <hi>To day thou ſhalt bee with mee in Paradiſe:</hi> Before God ſaid to the rich man,
<note place="margin">&amp; 12.20.</note> 
               <hi>This night thy ſoule ſhall bee required of thee;</hi> There the night is mentioned: death ſhall come ſuddenly upon him as an enemy, as a theefe, and finde him in greateſt ſecurity, in the dead ſleep of ſinne: Hee delighted in workes of darkneſſe, and ſhall bee caſt into utter darkneſſe; But here the day is named, <hi>To day thou ſhalt bee with mee;</hi> a day of ſalvation unto the good theefe, the firſt day of his life, and ſuch a day as never had any end. Chriſt is the true Light,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 1.9.</note> which lighteth every man
<pb n="272" facs="tcp:176251:144"/>comming into the world, with the light of reaſon; and everie Beleever with the light of happineſſe and glorie, when hee goeth out of this world into the holy Citie, that doth not need the Sun,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.23.</note> for the Lamb is the light thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To day.</hi> The perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of this gracious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe is limited to a ſhort time, and therefore all doubting is excluded. Our Saviour is crucified in the midſt, as nigh to one ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactour as the other: Both formerly were brethren in evill, conſenting in wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe; Both began to revile him before their death; yet one is rejected, and expoſed to vengeance, the other is taken as a
<pb n="273" facs="tcp:176251:144"/>brand ſnatcht out of the fire: Chriſt doth over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhadow him in mercy, and delivers not from death, but from condemnation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou ſhalt bee with Mee.</hi> A bleſſed change, to bee freed from the fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip of an impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent ſinner, a blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous reprobate, and to be admitted into the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety of Saints, yea for ever to be with the Lord; An unſpeakeable mercy, that hee, who by his owne confeſſion ſuffered juſtly, ſhould be with him who had done nothing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe. The righteous died for the ungodly, Chriſt for us ſinners; hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came Emmanuel, God with us, that wee may
<pb n="274" facs="tcp:176251:145"/>live with him in his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of glory.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou ſhalt bee with mee in Paradiſe.</hi> What wee gaine by the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> is much better than that wee loſt by the firſt; in the beginning <hi>Adam</hi> was in Paradiſe, but God was not with him, nor the feare of God before his eyes, when hee yeelded to the tempter: and hee was not with God, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dare hee appeare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him when hee wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in the Garden: Then the preſence of the Lord was a terrour unto <hi>Adam</hi> having ſinned; Now the preſence of Chriſt was the beſt of comforts un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the theefe being pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent.</p>
            <pb n="275" facs="tcp:176251:145"/>
            <p> Paradiſe it ſelfe was not Paradiſe unto <hi>Adam</hi> after hee had offended: But when wee ſhall bee ſet at liberty from the priſon of the grave, and acquitted from the ſting of death, wee ſhall bee as uncapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of ſinne, as of morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie; Oh then let us ever aſpire unto this moſt bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed eſtate. Although this good thiefe did ſuddenly, as it were with holy vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, breake into heaven (to ſhew that there is no end of the rich mercies of God) yet let not us preſume upon this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of grace, and ſo become examples of judgement unto others; Our whole life is given us to this end, that by
<pb n="276" facs="tcp:176251:146"/>patient continuance in well-doing, wee ſhould ſeeke for glory.</p>
            <p>The taſte of Gods good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in theſe outward be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits, ſhould excite and quicken our deſire to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the full fruition of eternall happineſſe: If we reſt contented in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities of this life, wee thinke the pleaſures of this life to bee as acceptable as the joyes above; As <hi>Lot</hi> thought the plaine of Jordan to bee as the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of the Lord:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 13.10.</note> And then wee cannot bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered from the common deſtruction, without the wonderfull mercy of God. But let us ſeeke a better countrie, even this cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiall Paradiſe: Strait is the
<pb n="277" facs="tcp:176251:146"/>gate, and narrow is the way that leadeth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto; and therefore our beſt diligence is required to find it; Yet, for our en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement, there are not Cherubims in the entrance to keep us from approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nigh unto it; but the Angel of the Covenant is the way whereby we muſt walke, and which doth guide us in the truth; And the doore whereby wee muſt enter, and which doth admit us that wee may bee ſaved: Yea, all the Angels rejoyce, when we enter into this path of life; and doe keep us in this way, miniſtring unto us the heires of ſalvation, who (as ſome have thought) were created to ſupply the
<pb n="278" facs="tcp:176251:147"/>defect of ſome of them, and to repaire the breach that their fall had made in this heavenly Paradiſe: There is not a flaming ſword turning every way, which may ſtrike a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour into us, that we ſhould not come neere; But the Sword of the Spirit is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven unto us, by which we may withſtand and van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh all enemies that ſhall encounter us in this our paſſage.</p>
            <p>There bee divers who goe to the Holy Land, which is now the ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of Gods wrath; but let our journey be to the Jeruſalem above, which is, and ever will be the Seat of Mercy, and the Throne of Glory. While other
<pb n="279" facs="tcp:176251:147"/>men labour to plat and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe the place where Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe was upon earth, let us ſeeke for this place that Chriſt is gone to prepare for us, into which when he comes againe he will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive us, that where hee is, wee may be alſo.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:176251:148"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Perlegi Librum hunc, cui titulus eſt</hi> [Adam in his Innocencie] <hi>atque illum typis mandari permitto.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Martis penult. 1637.</date> ex Aedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Londin.</dateline>
               <signed>SA. BAKER.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:176251:148"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
